<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- Main Guacamole page -->
<document xmlns="http://guac-dev.org/">

    <section>
        <notice>
            <title>What is Guacamole?</title>

        <!-- Demo video -->
        <youtube video="CHqgBfNiYh8">
            <para>Demo video of Guacamole 0.6.0.</para>
        </youtube>

        <para>
            Guacamole is an HTML5 web application that provides access to
            desktop environments using remote desktop protocols such as VNC or
            RDP. A centralized server acts as a tunnel and proxy, allowing
            access to multiple desktops through a web browser. No plugins are
            needed: the client requires nothing more than a web browser
            supporting HTML5 and AJAX.
        </para>

        </notice>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Downloads</title>

        <para>
            Pre-built bundles of packages for several Linux distributions are
            available. Depending on your distribution, installation
            instructions can be found on the Debian / Ubuntu Install
            Instructions or Fedora Install Instructions pages. If your
            distribution or platform is not currently supported, you can also
            build Guacamole and all its components from source, or install the
            old, Java-only version. See the instructions for installing the
            Java-only version of Guacamole.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Development</title>

        <para>
            Public discussion of development efforts is done over IRC at
            freenode.net on the #guacamole-dev channel. If you wish to develop
            a Guacamole-based web application, or to develop new protocol
            support plugins for guacd, please consult the API Documentation.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Support</title>

        <para>
            If you need (or wish to provide) help with Guacamole, there are
            forums on the SourceForge project page. You will need to register a
            username with SourceForge to use the forums. There is also an IRC
            channel on freenode.net dedicated to Guacamole support:
            #guacamole-help.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Reporting Problems</title>

        <para>
            If you think you've encountered a bug in Guacamole or any of its
            components, or you wish to request a feature, please create a new
            ticket at the Trac system hosted here. New tickets and comments are
            moderated to prevent spam. Be sure to provide your email address if
            you wish to be kept updated regarding progess.
        </para>
    </section>

</document>
