<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xml:id="history-of-guacamole"
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="en"
    xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

    <title>History</title>

    <indexterm>
        <primary>Guacamole</primary>
        <secondary>history</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <section>
        <title>RealMint</title>
        <para>Guacamole is now a generalized remote desktop gateway, but this
            was not always the case. Guacamole began as a purely text-based
            Telnet client written in JavaScript called <application
                xl:href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/realmint"
                >RealMint</application> ("RealMint" is an anagram for
            "terminal"). It was written mainly as a demonstration and, while
            intended to be useful, its main claim to fame was only that it was
            pure JavaScript.</para>
        <para>The tunnel used by RealMint was written in PHP. In contrast to
            Guacamole's HTTP tunnel, RealMint's tunnel used only simple
            long-polling and was inefficient. RealMint had a decent keyboard
            implementation which lives on now in parts of Guacamole's keyboard
            code, but this was really the extent of RealMint's features and
            usability.</para>
        <para>Given that it was just an implementation of a legacy protocol, and
            that several other JavaScript terminal emulators exist, most of
            which well-established and stable, the project was dropped.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>VNC Client</title>
        <para>Once the developers learned of the HTML5 canvas tag, and saw that
            it was already implemented in Firefox and Chrome, work started
            instead on a proof-of-concept JavaScript VNC client.</para>
        <para>This client was purely JavaScript with a Java server component,
            and worked by translating VNC into an XML-based version of the same.
            Its development was naturally driven by VNC's features, and its
            scope was limited to forwarding a single connection to a set of
            users. Although relatively slow, the proof-of-concept worked well
            enough that the project needed an online place to live, and was
            registered with SourceForge as "Guacamole" - an HTML5 VNC
            client.</para>
        <para>As Guacamole grew and became more than a proof-of-concept, the
            need for speed increased, and the old RealMint-style long polling
            was dropped, as was the use of XML.</para>
        <para>As WebSocket could not be trusted to be supported at the time, and
            Java had no WebSocket standard for servlets, an equivalent
            HTTP-based tunnel was developed.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Remote Desktop Gateway</title>
        <para>A faster text-based protocol was developed which could present the
            features of multiple remote desktop protocols, not just VNC. The
            entire system was rearchitected into a standard daemon, guacd, and a
            common library, libguac, which drove both the daemon and protocol
            support, which became extendable.</para>
        <para>The scope of the project expanded from an adequate VNC client to a
            performant HTML5 remote desktop gateway and general API. In its
            current state, Guacamole can be used as a central gateway to access
            any number of machines running different remote desktop servers. It
            provides extendable authentication, and in the case you need
            something more specialized, a general API for HTML5-based remote
            access.</para>
    </section>

</chapter>
