<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook V5.0//EN"
    "http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/dtd/docbook.dtd">

<chapter id="what-is-guacamole"
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="en"
    xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

    <title>What is Guacamole?</title>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>Guacamole</primary>
        <secondary>definition</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>
        Guacamole is a project that provides an HTML5 web application of
        the same name that provides access to desktop environments using
        remote desktop protocols (such as VNC or RDP). The project also
        provides an API that drives the flagship application, and can be
        used to power other similar applications or services.
    </para>

    <para>
        As a web application, Guacamole provides a centralized server which
        acts as a tunnel and proxy. Being written in JavaScript and using
        only HTML5 and other standards, Guacamole requires nothing more
        than a modern web browser or web-enabled device when accessing any
        of the desktops served.
    </para>

    <para>
        As an API, Guacamole provides a common and efficient means of
        streaming text data over a JavaScript-based tunnel (which need not
        use WebSocket), and a client implementation which supports the
        Guacamole protocol and renders the remote display when combined
        with a Guacamole protocol stream from the tunnel.
    </para>

    <para>
        It provides cross-browser mouse and keyboard events, an XML-driven
        on-screen keyboard, and synchronized nestable layers with
        hardware-accelerated compositing.
    </para>

    <para>
        Projects that wish to provide remote desktop support over HTML5 can
        leverage the years of research and development that went into
        Guacamole by incorporating the API into their application or
        service.
    </para>

</chapter>
