<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<chapter xml:id="quickconnect" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="en"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <title>Ad-hoc Connections</title>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>quickconnect</primary>
        <secondary>adhoc</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>The quickconnect extension provides a connection bar on the Guacamole Client home page
        that allows users to type in the URI of a server to which they want to connect and the client
        will parse the URI and immediately establish the connection.  The purpose of the extension is
        to allow situations where administrators want to allow users the flexibility of establishing
        their own connections without having to grant them access to edit connections or even to have
        to create the connections at all, aside from typing the URI.</para>
    <important>
        <para>There are several implications of using this extension that should be well-understood
            by administrators prior to implementing it:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para>Connections established with this extension are created in-memory
                    and only persist until the user logs out or the browser is closed.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Connections created with this extension are not accessible to other users, and
                    cannot be shared with other users.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>This extension provides no functionality for authenticating users - it does
                    not allow anonymous logins, and requires that users are successfully authenticated
                    by another authentication module before it can be used.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>The extension provides users the ability not only to establish connections, but
                    also to set any of the options for a connection.  There are security implications for
                    this - for example, RDP file sharing can be used to pass through any directory available
                    on the server running guacd to the remote desktop.  This should be taken into consideration
                    when enabling this extension and making sure that guacd is configured in a way that
                    does not compromise sensitive system files by allowing access to them.</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </important>
    <section xml:id="quickconnect-downloading">
        <title>Downloading the quickconnect extension</title>
        <para>The quickconnect extension is available separately from the main
                <filename>guacamole.war</filename>. The link for this and all other
            officially-supported and compatible extensions for a particular version of Guacamole are
            provided in the release notes for that version. You can find the release notes for
            current versions of Guacamole here: <link
                xlink:href="http://guacamole.apache.org/releases/"
                >http://guacamole.apache.org/releases/</link>.</para>
        <para>The quickconnect extension is packaged as a <filename>.tar.gz</filename> file containing
            only the extension itself, <filename>guacamole-auth-quickconnect-0.9.14.jar</filename>, which must
            ultimately be placed in <filename>GUACAMOLE_HOME/extensions</filename>.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="installing-quickconnect">
        <title>Installing the quickconnect extension</title>
        <para>Guacamole extensions are self-contained <filename>.jar</filename> files which are
            located within the <filename>GUACAMOLE_HOME/extensions</filename> directory.
                <emphasis>If you are unsure where <varname>GUACAMOLE_HOME</varname> is located on
                your system, please consult <xref linkend="configuring-guacamole"/> before
                proceeding.</emphasis></para>
        <para>To install the extension, you must:</para>
        <procedure>
            <step>
                <para>Create the <filename>GUACAMOLE_HOME/extensions</filename> directory, if it
                    does not already exist.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Place the <filename>guacamole-auth-quickconnect-0.9.14.jar</filename> file in
                    the <filename>GUACAMOLE_HOME/extensions</filename> directory.</para>
            </step>
        </procedure>
        <section xml:id="guac-quickconnect-config">
            <title>Configuring Guacamole for the quickconnect extension</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>configuring quickconnect</primary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>This module has no configuration options.</para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="completing-quickconnect-install">
            <title>Completing the installation</title>
            <para>Guacamole will only load newly-installed extensions during startup, so your
                servlet container will need to be restarted before the quickconnect extension
                can be used. <emphasis>Doing this will disconnect all active users, so be sure
                    that it is safe to do so prior to attempting installation.</emphasis>
                When ready, restart your servlet container and give the extension a try.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="using-quickconnect">
        <title>Using the quickconnect extension</title>
        <para>The quickconnect extension provides a field on the home page that allows you to enter
             a Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) to create a connection.  A URI is in the form:</para>
            <informalexample><replaceable>protocol</replaceable>://<replaceable>username</replaceable>
            :<replaceable>password</replaceable>@<replaceable>host</replaceable>:
            <replaceable>port</replaceable>/?<replaceable>options</replaceable></informalexample>
            <para>The <replaceable>protocol</replaceable> field can have any of the protocols supported by
            Guacamole, as documented in <xref linkend="configuring-guacamole"/>.  Many of the
            protocols define a default <replaceable>port</replaceable> value, with the exception of VNC.
            The <replaceable>options</replaceable> field can specify any of the protocol-specific
            options as documented on the configuration page.</para>
        <para>To establish a connection, simply type in a valid URI and either press "Enter" or click
            the connect button.  This extension will parse the URI and create a new connection, and
            immediately start that connection in the current browser.</para>
    </section>
</chapter>
