<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<chapter xml:id="administration" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="en"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <title>Administration</title>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>administration</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>Users and connections can be administered from within the web interface if the underlying
        authentication module supports this. The only officially-supported authentication module
        supporting this is the MySQL authentication provider, which is documented in a different
        chapter.</para>
    <para>If you are using the default authentication mechanism, this section does not apply to you,
        and the Guacamole web interface will appear as it did in past releases. If, on the other
        hand, you are using the MySQL authentication provider, and you are logged in as an
        administrator, you will see a "Manage" button next to the "Logout" button at the top of the
        screen.</para>
    <informalfigure>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/manage-button.png" format="PNG" contentwidth="3in"/>
            </imageobject>
            <caption>
                <para>The "Manage" button</para>
            </caption>
        </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
    <para>Clicking this button takes you to an administration screen where you can add or manipulate
        users and connections, depending on your permissions.</para>
    <section>
        <title>Managing users</title>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>user management</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>Once at the administration screen, you will see two sections displaying all visible
            users and connections. The visibility of these sections depends on your user's
            permissions. If you lack permission to manage users, the user management section will
            not display. The same goes for management of connections.</para>
        <para>To add a new user, type the username of the new user within the text box inside the
            user management section, and click the "Add" button. The new user will be added and made
            available. The new user will have no access to any existing connections, no
            administrative privileges, and no password, and will not be able to login. You will need
            to set the user's password first in order to allow login.</para>
        <informalfigure>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/manage-users.png" format="PNG" contentwidth="3in"/>
                </imageobject>
                <caption>
                    <para>User management interface</para>
                </caption>
            </mediaobject>
        </informalfigure>
        <para>To edit a user, just click on the user you wish to edit. A small dialog will display
            allowing you to change the user's password, add or remove administrative permissions,
            and add or remove access to specific connections or groups.</para>
        <para>If you have delete permission on the user, you will also see a "Delete" button.
            Clicking this button will permanently delete the user.</para>
        <informalfigure>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/edit-user.png" format="PNG" contentwidth="2in"/>
                </imageobject>
                <caption>
                    <para>Editing a user</para>
                </caption>
            </mediaobject>
        </informalfigure>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Managing connections</title>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>connection management</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>To add a new connection, click the "New Connection" button. A connection creation
            dialog will appear, allowing you to enter the details of the connection, such as its
            location, parameters, and name. This name should be descriptive, but must also be
            unique.</para>
        <para>Once you click "Save", the new connection will be added, but will initially only be
            usable by administrators and your current user. To add access to the new connection to
            another existing user, you must edit that user, checking the box corresponding to the
            new connection.</para>
        <informalfigure>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/manage-connections.png" format="PNG"
                        contentwidth="3in"/>
                </imageobject>
                <caption>
                    <para>Connection management interface</para>
                </caption>
            </mediaobject>
        </informalfigure>
        <para>Editing a connection works identically to editing a user. Click on the connection you
            wish to edit. A dialog will pop up displaying all parameters associated with the
            connection, allowing you to change the protocol, associated parameters, and to view the
            connection history.</para>
        <para>Connections can also be renamed or moved by altering the contents of the "Name" or
            "Location" fields.</para>
        <para>If you have delete permission on the connection, you will also see a "Delete" button.
            Clicking this button will permanently delete the connection.</para>
        <informalfigure>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/edit-connection.png" format="PNG" contentwidth="2in"
                    />
                </imageobject>
                <caption>
                    <para>Editing a connection</para>
                </caption>
            </mediaobject>
        </informalfigure>
        <section>
            <title>Grouping connections</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>connection groups</primary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>groups</primary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>Connections can be placed within groups for purposes of organization or load
                balancing. Each group is displayed in connection lists as a "+" symbol followed by
                its name. The group can be expanded revealing any contained connections or groups.
                If the group is a balancing group, the group can be used as a connection, and the
                least-used contained connection will be used.</para>
            <para>To add a new connection group, click the "New Group" button. A connection group
                creation dialog will appear, allowing you to enter the details of the group. Just as
                with connections, you can enter the location and name, which should be descriptive
                and unique. Duplicate names are not allowed.</para>
            <informalfigure>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/edit-group.png" format="PNG" contentwidth="3in"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption>
                        <para>Editing a connection group</para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </informalfigure>
            <para>You can edit existing connection groups by clicking on them within the
                administration interface, just like with users and connections. From within the
                dialog that appears, you can rename, move, and change the properties of existing
                connection groups.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Balancing vs. organizational groups</title>
            <para>Connection groups can be either "organizational" or "balancing". Each group can
                contain any number of other connections or groups, but the semantics of the group
                change depending on the type.</para>
            <para>An organizational group behaves exactly as a folder or directory in a file system.
                It simply contains connections and other groups, but provides no other behavior.
                Clicking on an organizational group within a connection list will expand the group,
                revealing its contents.</para>
            <para>A balancing group behaves as a connection. It dynamically balances load across the
                connections it contains, choosing the connection with the fewest number of active
                users. Unlike organizational groups, clicking on a balancing group causes a new
                connection to be opened. The actual underlying connection used depends on which
                connection has the least load at the time the group was clicked.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
</chapter>
