<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xml:id="guacamole-docker" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="en"
    xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <title>Installing Guacamole with Docker</title>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>docker</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>Guacamole can be deployed using Docker, removing the need to build
            <package>guacamole-server</package> from source. The Guacamole project provides
        officially-supported Docker images for both Guacamole and <package>guacd</package> which are
        kept up-to-date with each release.</para>
    <para>A typical Docker deployment of Guacamole will involve three separate containers, linked
        together at creation time:</para>
    <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
            <term><systemitem>glyptodon/guacd</systemitem></term>
            <listitem>
                <para>Provides the <package>guacd</package> daemon, built from the released
                        <package>guacamole-server</package> source with support for VNC, RDP, SSH,
                    and telnet.</para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term><systemitem>glyptodon/guacamole</systemitem></term>
            <listitem>
                <para>Provides the Guacamole web application running within Tomcat 8 with support
                    for WebSocket. The configuration necessary to connect to the linked
                        <package>guacd</package> container and MySQL or PostgreSQL database will be
                    generated automatically when the image starts.</para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
            <term><systemitem>mysql</systemitem> or <systemitem>postgresql</systemitem></term>
            <listitem>
                <para>Provides the database that Guacamole will use for authentication and storage
                    of connection configuration data.</para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>This separation is important, as it facilitates upgrades and maintains proper separation
        of concerns. With the database separate from Guacamole and <package>guacd</package>, those
        containers can be freely destroyed and recreated at will. The only container which must
        persist data through upgrades is the database.</para>
    <section xml:id="guacd-docker-image">
        <title>Running the <package>guacd</package> Docker image</title>
        <para>The <package>guacd</package> Docker image is built from the released
                <package>guacamole-server</package> source with support for VNC, RDP, SSH, and
            telnet. Common pitfalls like installing the required dependencies, installing fonts for
            SSH or telnet, and ensuring the FreeRDP plugins are installed to the correct location
            are all taken care of. It will simply just work.</para>
        <section xml:id="guacd-docker-guacamole">
            <title>Running <package>guacd</package> for use by the Guacamole Docker image</title>
            <para>When running the <package>guacd</package> image with the intent of linking to a
                Guacamole container, no ports need be exposed on the network. Access to these ports
                will be handled automatically by Docker during linking, and the Guacamole image will
                properly detect and configure the connection to <package>guacd</package>.</para>
            <informalexample>
                <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <command>docker</command> run --name <replaceable>some-guacd</replaceable> -d glyptodon/guacd</screen>
            </informalexample>
            <para>When run in this manner, <package>guacd</package> will be listening on its default
                port 4822, but this port will only be available to Docker containers that have been
                explicitly linked to
                <varname><replaceable>some-guacd</replaceable></varname>.</para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="guacd-docker-external">
            <title>Running <package>guacd</package> for use by services outside Docker</title>
            <para>If you are not going to use the Guacamole image, you can still leverage the
                    <package>guacd</package> image for ease of installation and maintenance. By
                exposing the <package>guacd</package> port, 4822, services external to Docker will
                be able to access <package>guacd</package>.</para>
            <important>
                <para><emphasis>Take great care when doing this</emphasis> -
                        <package>guacd</package> is a passive proxy and does not perform any kind of
                    authentication.</para>
                <para>If you do not properly isolate <package>guacd</package> from untrusted parts
                    of your network, malicious users may be able to use <package>guacd</package> as
                    a jumping point to other systems.</para>
            </important>
            <informalexample>
                <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <command>docker</command> run --name <replaceable>some-guacd</replaceable> -d -p 4822:4822 glyptodon/guacd</screen>
            </informalexample>
            <para><package>guacd</package> will now be listening on port 4822, and Docker will
                expose this port on the same server hosting Docker. Other services, such as an
                instance of Tomcat running outside of Docker, will be able to connect to
                    <package>guacd</package> directly.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="guacamole-docker-image">
        <title>The Guacamole Docker image</title>
        <para>The Guacamole Docker image is built on top of a standard Tomcat 8 image and takes care
            of all configuration automatically. When properly linked to a <package>guacd</package>
            container and either a PostgreSQL or MySQL database, the necessary Guacamole
            configuration will be automatically generated at startup.</para>
        <para>The name of the database and all associated credentials are specified with environment
            variables given when the container is created. All other configuration information is
            generated from the Docker links.</para>
        <important>
            <para><emphasis>You will need to initialize the database manually</emphasis>. Guacamole
                will not automatically create its own tables, but SQL scripts are provided to do
                this.</para>
        </important>
        <para>Once the Guacamole image is running, Guacamole will be accessible at
                    <uri>http://<replaceable>HOSTNAME</replaceable>:8080/guacamole/</uri>, where
                <replaceable>HOSTNAME</replaceable> is the hostname or address of the machine
            hosting Docker.</para>
        <section xml:id="guacamole-docker-mysql">
            <title>Deploying Guacamole with MySQL authentication</title>
            <para>Before deploying Guacamole with the intent of using MySQL for authentication,
                please ensure that you have each of the following already prepared:</para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>A Docker container running the <systemitem>glyptodon/guacd</systemitem>
                        image. Guacamole needs <package>guacd</package> in order to function, and
                        the Guacamole Docker image depends on a linked Docker container running
                            <package>guacd</package>.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>A Docker container running the <systemitem>mysql</systemitem>
                        image.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <section xml:id="initializing-guacamole-docker-mysql">
                <title>Initializing the MySQL database</title>
                <para>If your database is not already initialized with the Guacamole schema, you
                    will need to do so prior to using Guacamole. A convenience script for generating
                    the necessary SQL to do this is included in the Guacamole image.</para>
                <para>To generate a SQL script which can be used to initialize a fresh MySQL
                    database as documented in <xref linkend="jdbc-auth"/>:</para>
                <informalexample>
                    <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <command>docker</command> run --rm glyptodon/guacamole /opt/guacamole/bin/initdb.sh --mysql > <replaceable>initdb.sql</replaceable></screen>
                </informalexample>
                <para>Alternatively, you can use the SQL scripts included with the database
                    authentication.</para>
                <para>Once this script is generated, you must:</para>
                <procedure>
                    <step>
                        <para>Create a database for Guacamole within MySQL, such as
                                    <database><replaceable>guacamole_db</replaceable></database>.</para>
                    </step>
                    <step>
                        <para>Create a user for Guacamole within MySQL with access to this database,
                            such as
                                <systemitem><replaceable>guacamole_user</replaceable></systemitem>.</para>
                    </step>
                    <step>
                        <para>Run the script on the newly-created database. The process for doing
                            this via the <command>mysql</command> utility included with MySQL is
                            documented in <xref linkend="jdbc-auth"/>.</para>
                    </step>
                </procedure>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title xml:id="deploying-guacamole-docker-mysql">Deploying Guacamole</title>
                <para>Linking Guacamole to MySQL will require three environment variables. These
                    variables collectively describe how Guacamole will connect to MySQL:</para>
                <informaltable frame="all">
                    <tgroup cols="2">
                        <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>
                        <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="4*"/>
                        <thead>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Variable</entry>
                                <entry>Description</entry>
                            </row>
                        </thead>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry><envar>MYSQL_DATABASE</envar></entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <para>The name of the database to use for Guacamole
                                        authentication.</para>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><envar>MYSQL_USER</envar></entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <para>The user that Guacamole will use to connect to
                                        MySQL.</para>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><envar>MYSQL_PASSWORD</envar></entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <para>The password that Guacamole will provide when connecting
                                        to MySQL as <envar>MYSQL_USER</envar>.</para>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </informaltable>
                <para>Once your <package>guacd</package> container is ready, and the values of the
                    above variables are known, Guacamole can be deployed through Docker:</para>
                <informalexample>
                    <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <command>docker</command> run --name <replaceable>some-guacamole</replaceable> --link <replaceable>some-guacd</replaceable>:guacd \
    --link <replaceable>some-mysql</replaceable>:mysql      \
    -e MYSQL_DATABASE=<replaceable>guacamole_db</replaceable>  \
    -e MYSQL_USER=<replaceable>guacamole_user</replaceable>    \
    -e MYSQL_PASSWORD=<replaceable>some_password</replaceable> \
    -d -p 8080:8080 glyptodon/guacamole</screen>
                </informalexample>
                <para>If any of the configuration environment variables are omitted, you will
                    receive an error message, and the image will stop. You will then need to
                    recreate the container with the proper variables specified.</para>
            </section>
            <section xml:id="verifying-guacamole-docker-mysql">
                <title>Verifying the Guacamole install</title>
                <para>Now that the Guacamole image is running, Guacamole should be accessible at
                            <uri>http://<replaceable>HOSTNAME</replaceable>:8080/guacamole/</uri>,
                    where <replaceable>HOSTNAME</replaceable> is the hostname or address of the
                    machine hosting Docker.</para>
                <para>If you cannot access Guacamole, check the logs using Docker to determine if
                    something is wrong. Configuration parameters may have been given incorrectly, or
                    the database may be improperly initialized:</para>
                <informalexample>
                    <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <command>docker</command> logs <replaceable>some-guacamole</replaceable></screen>
                </informalexample>
                <para>If Guacamole has been successfully installed, you will see the Guacamole login
                    screen. The database initialization scripts will create the default
                    administrative user as "<systemitem>guacadmin</systemitem>" with the password
                        "<systemitem>guacadmin</systemitem>". You should change your password
                    immediately after verifying that your login works.</para>
                <para>Once you have verified Guacamole has been deployed successfully, you can
                    configure Guacamole through the web interface as described in <xref
                        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" linkend="administration"
                    />.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="guacamole-docker-postgresql">
            <title>Deploying Guacamole with PostgreSQL authentication</title>
            <para>Before deploying Guacamole with the intent of using PostgreSQL for authentication,
                please ensure that you have each of the following already prepared:</para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>A Docker container running the <systemitem>glyptodon/guacd</systemitem>
                        image. Guacamole needs <package>guacd</package> in order to function, and
                        the Guacamole Docker image depends on a linked Docker container running
                            <package>guacd</package>.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>A Docker container running the <systemitem>postgresql</systemitem>
                        image.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <section xml:id="initializing-guacamole-docker-postgresql">
                <title>Initializing the PostgreSQL database</title>
                <para>If your database is not already initialized with the Guacamole schema, you
                    will need to do so prior to using Guacamole. A convenience script for generating
                    the necessary SQL to do this is included in the Guacamole image.</para>
                <para>To generate a SQL script which can be used to initialize a fresh PostgreSQL
                    database as documented in <xref linkend="jdbc-auth"/>:</para>
                <informalexample>
                    <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <command>docker</command> run --rm glyptodon/guacamole /opt/guacamole/bin/initdb.sh --postgresql > <replaceable>initdb.sql</replaceable></screen>
                </informalexample>
                <para>Alternatively, you can use the SQL scripts included with the database
                    authentication.</para>
                <para>Once this script is generated, you must:</para>
                <procedure>
                    <step>
                        <para>Create a database for Guacamole within PostgreSQL, such as
                                    <database><replaceable>guacamole_db</replaceable></database>.</para>
                    </step>
                    <step>
                        <para>Run the script on the newly-created database.</para>
                    </step>
                    <step>
                        <para>Create a user for Guacamole within PostgreSQL with access to the
                            tables and sequences of this database, such as
                                    <systemitem><replaceable>guacamole_user</replaceable></systemitem>.</para>
                    </step>
                </procedure>
                <para>The process for doing this via the <command>psql</command> and
                        <command>createdb</command> utilities included with PostgreSQL is documented
                    in <xref linkend="jdbc-auth"/>.</para>
            </section>
            <section xml:id="deploying-guacamole-docker-postgresql">
                <title>Deploying Guacamole</title>
                <para>Linking Guacamole to your PostgreSQL database will require three environment
                    variables. These variables collectively describe how Guacamole will connect to
                    PostgreSQL:</para>
                <informaltable frame="all">
                    <tgroup cols="2">
                        <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>
                        <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="4*"/>
                        <thead>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Variable</entry>
                                <entry>Description</entry>
                            </row>
                        </thead>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry><envar>POSTGRES_DATABASE</envar></entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <para>The name of the database to use for Guacamole
                                        authentication.</para>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><envar>POSTGRES_USER</envar></entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <para>The user that Guacamole will use to connect to
                                        PostgreSQL.</para>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><envar>POSTGRES_PASSWORD</envar></entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <para>The password that Guacamole will provide when connecting
                                        to PostgreSQL as <envar>POSTGRES_USER</envar>.</para>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </informaltable>
                <para>Once your <package>guacd</package> container is ready, and the values of the
                    above variables are known, Guacamole can be deployed through Docker:</para>
                <informalexample>
                    <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <command>docker</command> run --name <replaceable>some-guacamole</replaceable> --link <replaceable>some-guacd</replaceable>:guacd \
    --link <replaceable>some-postgres</replaceable>:postgres      \
    -e POSTGRES_DATABASE=<replaceable>guacamole_db</replaceable>  \
    -e POSTGRES_USER=<replaceable>guacamole_user</replaceable>    \
    -e POSTGRES_PASSWORD=<replaceable>some_password</replaceable> \
    -d -p 8080:8080 glyptodon/guacamole</screen>
                </informalexample>
                <para>If any of the configuration environment variables are omitted, you will
                    receive an error message, and the image will stop. You will then need to
                    recreate the container with the proper variables specified.</para>
            </section>
            <section xml:id="verifying-guacamole-docker-postgresql">
                <title>Verifying the Guacamole install</title>
                <para>Now that the Guacamole image is running, Guacamole should be accessible at
                            <uri>http://<replaceable>HOSTNAME</replaceable>:8080/guacamole/</uri>,
                    where <replaceable>HOSTNAME</replaceable> is the hostname or address of the
                    machine hosting Docker.</para>
                <para>If you cannot access Guacamole, check the logs using Docker to determine if
                    something is wrong. Configuration parameters may have been given incorrectly, or
                    the database may be improperly initialized:</para>
                <informalexample>
                    <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <command>docker</command> logs <replaceable>some-guacamole</replaceable></screen>
                </informalexample>
                <para>If Guacamole has been successfully installed, you will see the Guacamole login
                    screen. The database initialization scripts will create the default
                    administrative user as "<systemitem>guacadmin</systemitem>" with the password
                        "<systemitem>guacadmin</systemitem>". You should change your password
                    immediately after verifying that your login works.</para>
                <para>Once you have verified Guacamole has been deployed successfully, you can
                    configure Guacamole through the web interface as described in <xref
                        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" linkend="administration"
                    />.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
    </section>
</chapter>
