<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<chapter xml:id="duo-auth" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="en"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <title>Duo two-factor authentication</title>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>Duo</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>Guacamole supports Duo as a second authentication factor, layered on top of any other
        authentication extension, including those available from the main project website. The Duo
        authentication extension allows users to be additionally verified against the Duo service
        before the authentication process is allowed to succeed.</para>
    <important>
        <para>This chapter involves modifying the contents of <varname>GUACAMOLE_HOME</varname> -
            the Guacamole configuration directory. If you are unsure where
                <varname>GUACAMOLE_HOME</varname> is located on your system, please consult <xref
                linkend="configuring-guacamole"/> before proceeding.</para>
    </important>
    <section xml:id="duo-architecture">
        <title>How Duo works with Guacamole</title>
        <para>Guacamole provides support for Duo as a second authentication factor. To make use of
            the Duo authentication extension, some other authentication mechanism will need be
            configured, as well. When a user attempts to log into Guacamole, other installed
            authentication methods will be queried first:</para>
        <informalfigure>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/duo-auth-factor-1.png" format="PNG"
                        contentwidth="2in"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </informalfigure>
        <para>Only after authentication has succeeded with one of those methods will Guacamole reach
            out to Duo to obtain additional verification of user identity:</para>
        <informalfigure>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/duo-auth-factor-2.png" format="PNG"
                        contentwidth="4in"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </informalfigure>
        <para>If both the initial authentication attempt and verification through Duo succeed, the
            user will be allowed in. If either mechanism fails, access to Guacamole is
            denied.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="duo-downloading">
        <title>Downloading the Duo extension</title>
        <para>The Duo authentication extension is available separately from the main
                <filename>guacamole.war</filename>. The link for this and all other
            officially-supported and compatible extensions for a particular version of Guacamole are
            provided on the release notes for that version. You can find the release notes for
            current versions of Guacamole here: <link
                xlink:href="http://guacamole.incubator.apache.org/releases/"
                >http://guacamole.incubator.apache.org/releases/</link>.</para>
        <para>The Duo authentication extension is packaged as a <filename>.tar.gz</filename> file
            containing only the extension itself,
                <filename>guacamole-auth-duo-0.9.11-incubating.jar</filename>, which must ultimately
            be placed in <filename>GUACAMOLE_HOME/extensions</filename>.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="installing-duo-auth">
        <title>Installing Duo authentication</title>
        <para>Guacamole extensions are self-contained <filename>.jar</filename> files which are
            located within the <filename>GUACAMOLE_HOME/extensions</filename> directory. To install
            the Duo authentication extension, you must:</para>
        <procedure>
            <step>
                <para>Create the <filename>GUACAMOLE_HOME/extensions</filename> directory, if it
                    does not already exist.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Copy <filename>guacamole-auth-duo-0.9.11-incubating.jar</filename> within
                        <filename>GUACAMOLE_HOME/extensions</filename>.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Configure Guacamole to use Duo authentication, as described below.</para>
            </step>
        </procedure>
        <important>
            <para>You will need to restart Guacamole by restarting your servlet container in order
                to complete the installation. Doing this will disconnect all active users, so be
                sure that it is safe to do so prior to attempting installation. If you do not
                configure the Duo authentication properly, Guacamole will not start up again until
                the configuration is fixed.</para>
        </important>
        <section>
            <title xml:id="duo-guac-config">Adding Guacamole to Duo</title>
            <para>Duo does not provide a specific integration option for Guacamole, but Guacamole's
                Duo extension uses Duo's generic authentication API. To use Guacamole with Duo, you
                will need to add it as a new "Auth API" application from within the "Applications"
                tab of the admin panel of your Duo account:</para>
            <informalfigure>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/duo-add-guacamole.png" format="PNG"
                            contentwidth="6in"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </informalfigure>
            <para>Within the settings of the newly-added application, rename the application to
                something more representative than "Auth API". This application name is what will be
                presented to your users when they are prompted by Duo for additional
                authentication:</para>
            <informalfigure>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/duo-rename-guacamole.png" format="PNG"
                            contentwidth="6in"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </informalfigure>
            <para>Once you've finished adding Guacamole as an "Auth API" application, the
                configuration information required to configure Guacamole is listed within the
                application's "Details" section. You will need to copy the integration key, secret
                key, and API hostname - they will later be specified within
                    <filename>guacamole.properties</filename>:</para>
            <informalfigure>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/duo-copy-details.png" format="PNG"
                            contentwidth="6in"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </informalfigure>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="guac-duo-config">
            <title>Configuring Guacamole for Duo</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>configuring Duo</primary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>Duo</primary>
                <secondary>configuration</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>The application-specific configuration information retrieved from Duo must be
                added to <filename>guacamole.properties</filename> to describe how Guacamole should
                connect to the Duo service:</para>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><property>duo-api-hostname</property></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The hostname of the Duo API endpoint to be used to verify user
                            identities. This will usually be in the form
                                    "<uri>api-<replaceable>XXXXXXXX</replaceable>.duosecurity.com</uri>",
                            where "<replaceable>XXXXXXXX</replaceable>" is some arbitrary
                            alphanumeric value assigned by Duo. This value will have been generated
                            by Duo when you added Guacamole as an "Auth API" application, and can be
                            found within the application details in the "API hostname" field.
                                <emphasis>This value is required.</emphasis></para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><property>duo-integration-key</property></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The integration key provided for Guacamole by Duo. This value will
                            have been generated by Duo when you added Guacamole as an "Auth API"
                            application, and can be found within the application details in the
                            "Integration key" field. <emphasis>This value is required and must be
                                EXACTLY 20 characters.</emphasis></para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><property>duo-secret-key</property></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The secret key provided for Guacamole by Duo. This value will have
                            been generated by Duo when you added Guacamole as an "Auth API"
                            application, and can be found within the application details in the
                            "Secret key" field. <emphasis>This value is required and must be EXACTLY
                                20 characters.</emphasis></para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <para>In addition to the above, <emphasis>you must also manually generate an
                    "application key"</emphasis>. The application key is required by Duo's
                authentication API, but is not provided by Duo. It is an arbitrary value meant to be
                unique to each deployment of an application using their API.</para>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><property>duo-application-key</property></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>An arbitrary, random key which you manually generated for Guacamole.
                                <emphasis>This value is required and must be AT LEAST 40
                                characters.</emphasis></para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <para>The application key can be generated with any method as long as it is sufficiently
                random. There exist utilities which will do this for you, like
                    <command>pwgen</command>:</para>
            <informalexample>
                <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>pwgen 40 1</userinput>
<computeroutput>em1io4zievohneeseiwah0zie2raQuoo2ci5oBoo</computeroutput>
<prompt>$</prompt></screen>
            </informalexample>
            <para>Alternatively, one quick and fairly portable way to do this is to use the
                    <command>dd</command> utility to copy random bytes from the secure random device
                    <filename>/dev/random</filename>, sending the data through a cryptographic hash
                tool with a sufficiently-long result, like <command>sha256sum</command>:</para>
            <informalexample>
                <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>dd if=/dev/random count=1 | sha256sum</userinput>
<computeroutput>5d16d6bb86da73e7d1abd3286b21dcf3b3e707532e64ceebc7a008350d0d485d -</computeroutput>
<prompt>$</prompt></screen>
            </informalexample>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="completing-duo-install">
            <title>Completing the installation</title>
            <para>Guacamole will only reread <filename>guacamole.properties</filename> and load
                newly-installed extensions during startup, so your servlet container will need to be
                restarted before Duo authentication will take effect. Restart your servlet container
                and give the new authentication a try.</para>
            <para>
                <important>
                    <para>You only need to restart your servlet container. <emphasis>You do not need
                            to restart <package>guacd</package></emphasis>.</para>
                    <para><package>guacd</package> is completely independent of the web application
                        and does not deal with <filename>guacamole.properties</filename> or the
                        authentication system in any way. Since you are already restarting the
                        servlet container, restarting <package>guacd</package> as well technically
                        won't hurt anything, but doing so is completely pointless.</para>
                </important>
            </para>
            <para>If Guacamole does not come back online after restarting your servlet container,
                check the logs. Problems in the configuration of the Duo extension may prevent
                Guacamole from starting up, and any such errors will be recorded in the logs of your
                servlet container.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
</chapter>
