<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<chapter xml:id="event-listeners" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="en"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <title>Event listeners</title>
    <indexterm xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
        <primary>events</primary>
        <secondary>listeners</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>Guacamole supports the delivery of event notifications to custom extensions.
        Developers can use listener extensions to integrate custom handling of events such as 
        successful and failed authentications, and requests to connect and disconnect tunnels to 
        desktop environments.</para>
    <para>A listener extension could be used, for example, to record authentication attempts in 
        an external database for security auditing or alerting. By listening to tunnel lifecycle 
        events, a listener extension could be used to help coordinate startup and shutdown of 
        machine resources; particularly useful in cloud environments where minimizing 
        running-but-idle resources is an important cost savings measure.</para>
    <para>For certain <emphasis>vetoable</emphasis> events, an event listener can even influence
        Guacamole's behavior. For example, a listener can veto a successful authentication,
        effectively causing the authentication to be considered failed. Similarly, a listener 
        can veto a tunnel connection, effectively preventing the tunnel from being connected to
        a virtual desktop resource.</para>
    <para>Custom event listeners are packaged using the same extension mechanism used for
        custom authentication providers. A single listener extension can include any number of 
        classes that implement the listener interface. A single extension module can also include
        any combination of authentication providers and listeners, so developers can easily
        combine authentication providers with listeners designed to support them.</para>
    <para>To demonstrate the principles involved in receiving Guacamole event notifications, we 
        will implement a simple listener extension that logs authentication events. While our 
        approach simply writes event details to the same log used by the Guacamole web application, 
        a listener could process these events in arbitrary ways, limited only by the imagination and
        ingenuity of the developer.</para>
    <section xml:id="custom-event-listener-skeleton">
        <title>A Guacamole listener extension skeleton</title>
        <para>For simplicity's sake, and because this is how things are done upstream in the
            Guacamole project, we will use Maven to build our extension.</para>
        <para>The bare minimum required for a Guacamole listener extension is a
                <filename>pom.xml</filename> file listing guacamole-ext as a dependency, a single
            <filename>.java</filename> file implementing our stub of a listener, and a
                <filename>guac-manifest.json</filename> file describing the extension and pointing
            to our listener class.</para>
        <example>
            <title>Barebones <filename>pom.xml</filename> required for a simple listener
                extension that writes log messages for received events.</title>
            <programlisting>&lt;project xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/POM/4.0.0"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/POM/4.0.0
                        http://maven.apache.org/maven-v4_0_0.xsd">

    &lt;modelVersion>4.0.0&lt;/modelVersion>
    &lt;groupId>org.apache.guacamole&lt;/groupId>
    &lt;artifactId>guacamole-listener-tutorial&lt;/artifactId>
    &lt;packaging>jar&lt;/packaging>
    &lt;version>1.0.0&lt;/version>
    &lt;name>guacamole-listener-tutorial&lt;/name>

    &lt;properties>
        &lt;project.build.sourceEncoding>UTF-8&lt;/project.build.sourceEncoding>
    &lt;/properties>

    &lt;build>
        &lt;plugins>

            &lt;!-- Written for 1.6 -->
            &lt;plugin>
                &lt;groupId>org.apache.maven.plugins&lt;/groupId>
                &lt;artifactId>maven-compiler-plugin&lt;/artifactId>
                &lt;version>3.3&lt;/version>
                &lt;configuration>
                    &lt;source>1.6&lt;/source>
                    &lt;target>1.6&lt;/target>
                &lt;/configuration>
            &lt;/plugin>

        &lt;/plugins>
    &lt;/build>

    &lt;dependencies>

        &lt;!-- Guacamole Extension API -->
        &lt;dependency>
            &lt;groupId>org.apache.guacamole&lt;/groupId>
            &lt;artifactId>guacamole-ext&lt;/artifactId>
            &lt;version>1.0.0&lt;/version>
            &lt;scope>provided&lt;/scope>
        &lt;/dependency>

        &lt;!-- Slf4j API -->
        &lt;!-- This is needed only if your listener wants to 
                write to the Guacamole web application log -->
        &lt;dependency>
            &lt;groupId>org.slf4j&lt;/groupId>
            &lt;artifactId>slf4j-api&lt;/artifactId>
            &lt;version>1.7.7&lt;/version>
            &lt;scope>provided&lt;/scope>
        &lt;/dependency>

    &lt;/dependencies>

&lt;/project></programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>Naturally, we need the actual listener extension skeleton code. While you can
            put this in whatever file and package you want, for the sake of this tutorial, we will
            assume you are using
                <classname>org.apache.guacamole.event.TutorialListener</classname>.</para>
        <para>For now, we won't actually do anything other than log the fact that an event 
            notification was received. At this point, we're just creating the skeleton for our 
            listener extension.</para>                
        <example>
            <title>A skeleton <classname>TutorialListener</classname></title>
            <programlisting>package org.apache.guacamole.event;

import org.apache.guacamole.GuacamoleException;
import org.apache.guacamole.net.event.listener.Listener;
import org.slf4j.Logger;
import org.slf4j.LoggerFactory;

/**
 * A Listener implementation intended to demonstrate basic use
 * of Guacamole's listener extension API.
 */
public class TutorialListener implements Listener {

    private static final Logger logger = 
         LoggerFactory.getLogger(TutorialListener.class);

    @Override
    public void handleEvent(Object event) throws GuacamoleException {
        logger.info("received Guacamole event notification");
    }

}</programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>To conform with Maven, this skeleton file must be placed within
                <filename>src/main/java/org/apache/guacamole/event</filename> as
                <filename>TutorialListener.java</filename>.</para>
        <para>As you can see, implementing a listener is quite simple. There is a single 
            <classname>Listener</classname> interface to implement. All Guacamole event
            notifications will be delivered to your code by invoking the 
            <methodname>handleEvent</methodname> method. We will see shortly how to use
            the passed event object to get the details of the event itself.
        </para>
        <para>The only remaining piece for the overall skeleton to be complete is a
                <filename>guac-manifest.json</filename> file. <emphasis>This file is absolutely
                required for all Guacamole extensions.</emphasis> The
                <filename>guac-manifest.json</filename> format is described in more detail in <xref
                xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" linkend="guacamole-ext"/>. It provides
            for quite a few properties, but for our listener extension we are mainly
            interested in the Guacamole version sanity check (to make sure an extension built for
            the API of Guacamole version X is not accidentally used against version Y) and telling
            Guacamole where to find our listener class.</para>
        <para>The Guacamole extension format requires that <filename>guac-manifest.json</filename>
            be placed in the root directory of the extension <filename>.jar</filename> file. To
            accomplish this with Maven, we place it within the
                <filename>src/main/resources</filename> directory. Maven will automatically pick it
            up during the build and include it within the <filename>.jar</filename>.</para>
        <example>
            <title>The required <filename>guac-manifest.json</filename></title>
            <programlisting>{

    "guacamoleVersion" : "1.0.0",

    "name"      : "Tutorial Listener Extension",
    "namespace" : "guac-listener-tutorial",

    "listeners" : [
        "org.apache.guacamole.event.TutorialListener"
    ]

}</programlisting>
        </example>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="custom-listener-building">
        <title>Building the extension</title>
        <para>Once all three of the above files are in place, the extension should build successfully
            even though it is just a skeleton at this point.</para>
        <informalexample>
            <screen><prompt>$</prompt> mvn package
<computeroutput>[INFO] Scanning for projects...
[INFO] ---------------------------------------------------------------
[INFO] Building guacamole-listener-tutorial 1.0.0
[INFO] ---------------------------------------------------------------
...
[INFO] ---------------------------------------------------------------
[INFO] BUILD SUCCESS
[INFO] ---------------------------------------------------------------
[INFO] Total time: 1.297 s
[INFO] Finished at: 2017-10-08T13:12:39-04:00
[INFO] Final Memory: 19M/306M
[INFO] ---------------------------------------------------------------</computeroutput>
<prompt>$</prompt></screen>
        </informalexample>
        <para>Assuming you see the "<computeroutput>BUILD SUCCESS</computeroutput>" message when you
            build the extension, there will be a new file,
                <filename>target/guacamole-listener-tutorial-1.0.0.jar</filename>, which can be
            installed within Guacamole (see <xref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                linkend="custom-listener-installing"/> at the end of this chapter). It should log
            event notifications that occur during, for example, authentication attempts.
            If you changed the name or version of the project
            in the <filename>pom.xml</filename> file, the name of this new <filename>.jar</filename>
            file will be different, but it can still be found within
            <filename>target/</filename>.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="custom-listener-event-handling">
        <title>Handling events</title>
        <para>The Guacamole <classname>Listener</classname> interface represents a low-level event
            handling API. A listener is notified of every event generated by Guacamole. The listener
            must examine the event type to determine whether the event is of interest, and if so to 
            dispatch the event to the appropriate entry point.</para>
        <para>The event types that can be produced by Guacamole are described in the 
            <package>org.apache.guacamole.net.event</package> package of the <package>guacamole-ext</package>
            API. In this package you will find several concrete event types as well as interfaces that 
            describe common characteristics of certain of event types. You can use any of these types 
            to distinguish the events received by your listener, and to examine properties of an event 
            of a given type.</para>
        <para>Suppose we wish to log authentication success and failure events, while ignoring all other
            event types. The <classname>AuthenticationSuccessEvent</classname> and 
            <classname>AuthenticationFailureEvent</classname> types are used to notify a listener
            of authentication events. We can simply check whether a received event is of one of
            these types and, if so, log an appropriate message.</para>
        <example>
            <title>Using the event type to log an authentication success or failure</title>
            <programlisting>package org.apache.guacamole.event;

import org.apache.guacamole.GuacamoleException;
import org.apache.guacamole.net.event.AuthenticationFailureEvent;
import org.apache.guacamole.net.event.AuthenticationSuccessEvent;
import org.apache.guacamole.net.event.listener.Listener;
import org.slf4j.Logger;
import org.slf4j.LoggerFactory;

/**
 * A Listener that logs authentication success and failure events.
 */
public class TutorialListener implements Listener {

    private static final Logger logger = 
        LoggerFactory.getLogger(TutorialListener.class);

    @Override
    public void handleEvent(Object event) throws GuacamoleException {

        if (event instanceof AuthenticationSuccessEvent) {
            logger.info("successful authentication for user {}", 
                ((AuthenticationSuccessEvent) event)
                    .getCredentials().getUsername());
        }
        else if (event instanceof AuthenticationFailureEvent) {
            logger.info("failed authentication for user {}", 
                ((AuthenticationFailureEvent) event)
                    .getCredentials().getUsername());
        }
    }

}</programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>In our example, we use <code>instanceof</code> to check for the two event types of
        interest to our listener. Once we have identified an event of interest, we can safely
        cast the event type to access properties of the event.</para>
        <para>The extension is now complete and can be built as described earlier in <xref
                xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" linkend="custom-listener-building"/>
            and installed as described below in <xref
                xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" linkend="custom-listener-installing"/>.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="custom-listener-veto">
        <title>Influencing Guacamole by event veto</title>
        <para>An implementation of the <methodname>handleEvent</methodname> method is permitted to
            throw any <classname>GuacamoleException</classname>. For certain <emphasis>vetoable</emphasis>
            event types, throwing a <classname>GuacamoleException</classname> serves to effectively 
            veto the action that resulted in the event notification. See the API documentation for
            <package>guacamole-ext</package> to learn more about vetoable event types.</para>
        <para>As an (admittedly contrived) example, suppose we want to prevent a user named 
            "guacadmin" from accessing Guacamole. For whatever reason, we don't wish to remove or disable 
            the auth database entry for this user. In this case we can use a listener to "blacklist" this
            user, preventing access to Guacamole. In the listener, when we get an 
            <classname>AuthenticationSuccessEvent</classname> we can check to see if the user is 
            "guacadmin" and, if so, throw an exception to prevent this user from logging in to 
            Guacamole.</para>
        <example>
            <title>Vetoing an event by throwing a <classname>GuacamoleException</classname></title>
            <programlisting>package org.apache.guacamole.event;

import org.apache.guacamole.GuacamoleException;
import org.apache.guacamole.GuacamoleSecurityException;
import org.apache.guacamole.net.event.AuthenticationFailureEvent;
import org.apache.guacamole.net.event.AuthenticationSuccessEvent;
import org.apache.guacamole.net.event.listener.Listener;
import org.slf4j.Logger;
import org.slf4j.LoggerFactory;

/**
 * A Listener that logs authentication success and failure events
 * and prevents the "guacadmin" user from logging in by throwing
 * a GuacamoleSecurityException.
 */
public class TutorialListener implements Listener {

    private static final Logger logger = 
        LoggerFactory.getLogger(TutorialListener.class);

    @Override
    public void handleEvent(Object event) throws GuacamoleException {

        if (event instanceof AuthenticationSuccessEvent) {
          final String username = ((AuthenticationSuccessEvent) event)
              .getCredentials().getUsername();

          if ("guacadmin".equals(username)) {
            logger.warn("user {} is blacklisted", username);
            throw new GuacamoleSecurityException(
                "User '" + username + "' is blacklisted");
          }

          logger.info("successful authentication for user {}", username);
        }
        else if (event instanceof AuthenticationFailureEvent) {
            logger.info("failed authentication for user {}", 
                ((AuthenticationFailureEvent) event)
                    .getCredentials().getUsername());
        }
    }

}</programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>If our Guacamole user database contains a user named "guacadmin", and we build and 
            install this listener extension, we will find that an attempt to log in as this user
            now results in a message in the UI indicating that the user is blacklisted. If we
            examine the Guacamole log, we will see the message indicating that the user is 
            blacklisted. Because the successful authentication was vetoed, Guacamole sends a
            subsequent authentication failure notification, which we see logged as well.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="custom-listener-installing">
        <title>Installing the extension</title>
        <para>Guacamole extensions are self-contained <filename>.jar</filename> files which are
            installed by being placed within <filename>GUACAMOLE_HOME/extensions</filename>, and
            this extension is no different. As described in <xref
                xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" linkend="configuring-guacamole"/>,
                <varname>GUACAMOLE_HOME</varname> is a placeholder used to refer to the directory
            that Guacamole uses to locate its configuration files and extensions. Typically, this
            will be the <filename>.guacamole</filename> directory within the home directory of the
            user running Tomcat.</para>
        <para>To install your extension, copy the
            <filename>target/guacamole-listener-tutorial-1.0.0.jar</filename> file into
            <filename>GUACAMOLE_HOME/extensions</filename> and restart Tomcat. Guacamole will
            automatically load your extension, logging an informative message that it has done
            so:</para>
        <informalexample>
            <screen>Extension "Tutorial Listener Extension" loaded.</screen>
        </informalexample>
    </section>
</chapter>
