<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xml:id="guacamole-ext" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    version="5.0" xml:lang="en" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <title>guacamole-ext</title>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>API</primary>
        <secondary>Java</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>guacamole-ext</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>While not strictly part of the Java API provided by the Guacamole project, guacamole-ext
        is an API exposed by the Guacamole web application within a separate project such that
        extensions, specifically authentication providers, can be written to tweak Guacamole to fit
        well in existing deployments.</para>
    <para>Extensions to Guacamole can:</para>
    <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>Provide alternative authentication methods and sources of connection/user
                data.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Theme or brand Guacamole through additional CSS files and static resources.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Extend Guacamole's JavaScript code by providing JavaScript that will be loaded
                automatically.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Add additional display languages, or alter the translation strings of existing
                languages.</para>
        </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <section xml:id="extension-format">
        <title>Guacamole extension format</title>
        <para>Guacamole extensions are standard Java <filename>.jar</filename> files which contain
            all classes and resources required by the extension, as well as the Guacamole extension
            manifest. There is no set structure to an extension except that the manifest must be in
            the root of the archive. Java classes and packages, if any, will be read from the
                <filename>.jar</filename> relative to the root, as well.</para>
        <para>Beyond this, the semantics and locations associated with all other resources within
            the extension are determined by the extension manifest alone.</para>
        <section xml:id="extension-manifest">
            <title>Extension manifest</title>
            <para>The Guacamole extension manifest is a single JSON file,
                    <filename>guac-manifest.json</filename>, which describes the location of each
                resource, the type of each resource, and the version of Guacamole that the extension
                was built for. The manifest can contain the following properties:</para>
            <informaltable frame="all">
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>
                    <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="3*"/>
                    <thead>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Property</entry>
                            <entry>Description</entry>
                        </row>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry><property>guacamoleVersion</property></entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para>The version string of the Guacamole release that this
                                    extension is written for. <emphasis>This property is required
                                        for all extensions.</emphasis> The special version string
                                        <code>"*"</code> can be used if the extension does not
                                    depend on a particular version of Guacamole, but be careful -
                                    this will bypass version compatibility checks, and should never
                                    be used if the extension does more than basic theming or
                                    branding.</para>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><property>name</property></entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para>A human-readable name for the extension. <emphasis>This
                                        property is required for all extensions.</emphasis> When
                                    your extension is successfully loaded, a message acknowledging
                                    the successful loading of your extension by name will be
                                    logged.</para>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><property>namespace</property></entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para>A unique string which identifies your extension.
                                        <emphasis>This property is required for all
                                        extensions.</emphasis> This string should be unique enough
                                    that it is unlikely to collide with the namespace of any other
                                    extension.</para>
                                <para>If your extension contains static resources, those resources
                                    will be served at a path derived from the namespace provided
                                    here.</para>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><property>authProviders</property></entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para>An array of the classnames of all
                                        <classname>AuthenticationProvider</classname> subclasses
                                    provided by this extension.</para>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><property>js</property></entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para>An array of all JavaScript files within the extension. All
                                    paths within this array must be relative paths, and will be
                                    interpreted relative to the root of the archive.</para>
                                <para>JavaScript files declared here will be automatically loaded
                                    when the web application loads within the user's browser.</para>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><property>css</property></entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para>An array of all CSS files within the extension. All paths
                                    within this array must be relative paths, and will be
                                    interpreted relative to the root of the archive.</para>
                                <para>CSS files declared here will be automatically applied when the
                                    web application loads within the user's browser.</para>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><property>html</property></entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para>An array of all HTML files within the extension that should be
                                    used to update or replace existing HTML within the Guacamole
                                    interface. All paths within this array must be relative paths,
                                    and will be interpreted relative to the root of the
                                    archive.</para>
                                <para>HTML files declared here will be automatically applied to
                                    other HTML within the Guacamole interface when the web
                                    application loads within the user's browser. The manner in which
                                    the files are applied is dictated by <tag>&lt;meta ...></tag>
                                    within those same files.</para>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><property>translations</property></entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para>An array of all translation files within the extension. All
                                    paths within this array must be relative paths, and will be
                                    interpreted relative to the root of the archive.</para>
                                <para>Translation files declared here will be automatically added to
                                    the available languages. If a translation file provides a
                                    language that already exists within Guacamole, its strings will
                                    override the strings of the existing translation.</para>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><property>resources</property></entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para>An object where each property name is the name of a web
                                    resource file, and each value is the mimetype for that resource.
                                    All paths within this object must be relative paths, and will be
                                    interpreted relative to the root of the archive.</para>
                                <para>Web resources declared here will be made available to the
                                    application at
                                            <filename>app/ext/<replaceable>NAMESPACE</replaceable>/<replaceable>PATH</replaceable></filename>,
                                    where <replaceable>NAMESPACE</replaceable> is the value of the
                                        <property>namespace</property> property, and
                                        <replaceable>PATH</replaceable> is the declared web resource
                                    filename.</para>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </informaltable>
            <para>The only absolutely required properties are <property>guacamoleVersion</property>,
                    <property>name</property>, and <property>namespace</property>, as they are used
                to identify the extension and for compatibility checks. The most minimal
                    <filename>guac-manifest.json</filename> will look something like this:</para>
            <informalexample>
                <programlisting>{
    "guacamoleVersion" : "0.9.10-incubating",
    "name" : "My Extension",
    "namespace" : "my-extension"
}</programlisting>
            </informalexample>
            <para>This will allow the extension to load, but does absolutely nothing otherwise.
                Lacking the semantic information provided by the other properties, no other files
                within the extension will be used. A typical <filename>guac-manifest.json</filename>
                for an extension providing theming or branding would be more involved:</para>
            <informalexample>
                <programlisting>{

    "guacamoleVersion" : "0.9.10-incubating",

    "name"      : "My Extension",
    "namespace" : "my-extension",

    "css" : [ "theme.css" ],

    "html" : [ "loginDisclaimer.html" ],

    "resources" : {
        "images/logo.png"   : "image/png",
        "images/cancel.png" : "image/png",
        "images/delete.png" : "image/png"
    }

}</programlisting>
            </informalexample>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="patch-html">
            <title>Updating existing HTML</title>
            <para>The existing HTML structure of Guacamole's interface can be modified by extensions
                through special "patch" HTML files declared by the <property>html</property>
                property in <filename>guac-manifest.json</filename>. These files are HTML fragments
                and are identical to any other HTML file except that they contain Guacamole-specific
                    <tag>meta</tag> tags that instruct Guacamole to modify its own HTML in a
                particular way. Each <tag>meta</tag> tag takes the following form:</para>
            <informalexample>
                <programlisting>&lt;meta name="<replaceable>NAME</replaceable>" content="<replaceable>SELECTOR</replaceable>"></programlisting>
            </informalexample>
            <para>where <replaceable>SELECTOR</replaceable> is a CSS selector that matches the
                elements within the Guacamole interface that serve as a basis for the modification,
                and <replaceable>NAME</replaceable> is any one of the following defined
                modifications:</para>
            <informaltable frame="all">
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>
                    <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="4*"/>
                    <thead>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Name</entry>
                            <entry>Description</entry>
                        </row>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry><property>before</property></entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para>Inserts the specified HTML immediately before any element
                                    matching the CSS selector.</para>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><property>after</property></entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para>Inserts the specified HTML immediately after any element
                                    matching the CSS selector.</para>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><property>replace</property></entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para>Replaces any element matching the CSS selector with the
                                    specified HTML.</para>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><property>before-children</property></entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para>Inserts the specified HTML immediately before the first child
                                    (if any) of any element matching the CSS selector. If a matching
                                    element has no children, the HTML simply becomes the entire
                                    contents of the matching element.</para>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><property>after-children</property></entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para>Inserts the specified HTML immediately after the last child
                                    (if any) of any element matching the CSS selector. If a matching
                                    element has no children, the HTML simply becomes the entire
                                    contents of the matching element.</para>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><property>replace-children</property></entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para>Replaces the entire contents of any element matching the CSS
                                    selector with the specified HTML.</para>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </informaltable>
            <para>For example, to add a welcome message and link to some corporate privacy policy (a
                fairly common need), you would add an HTML file like the following:</para>
            <informalexample>
                <programlisting>&lt;meta name="after" content=".login-ui .login-dialog">

&lt;div class="welcome">
    &lt;h2>Welcome to our Guacamole server!&lt;/h2>
    &lt;p>
        Please be sure to read our &lt;a href="/path/to/some/privacy.html">privacy
        policy&lt;/a> before continuing.
    &lt;/p>
&lt;/div></programlisting>
            </informalexample>
            <para>After the extension is installed and Guacamole is restarted, the "welcome" div and
                its contents will automatically be inserted directly below the login dialog (the
                only element that would match <code>.login-ui .login-dialog</code>) as if they were
                part of Guacamole's HTML in the first place.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="environment">
        <title>Accessing the server configuration</title>
        <para>The configuration of the Guacamole server is exposed through the
                <classname>Environment</classname> interface, specifically the
                <classname>LocalEnvironment</classname> implementation of this interface. Through
                <classname>Environment</classname>, you can access all properties declared within
                <filename>guacamole.properties</filename>, determine the proper hostname/port of
                <package>guacd</package>, and access the contents of
                <varname>GUACAMOLE_HOME</varname>.</para>
        <section xml:id="simple-config">
            <title>Custom properties</title>
            <para>If your extension requires generic, unstructured configuration parameters,
                    <filename>guacamole.properties</filename> is a reasonable and simple location
                for them. The <classname>Environment</classname> interface provides direct access to
                    <filename>guacamole.properties</filename> and simple mechanisms for reading and
                parsing the properties therein. The value of a property can be retrieved calling
                    <methodname>getProperty()</methodname>, which will return
                    <constant>null</constant> or a default value for undefined properties, or
                    <methodname>getRequiredProperty()</methodname>, which will throw an exception
                for undefined properties.</para>
            <para>For convenience, guacamole-ext contains several pre-defined property base classes
                for common types:</para>
            <informaltable frame="all">
                <tgroup cols="3">
                    <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="2*"/>
                    <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="1*"/>
                    <colspec colname="c3" colnum="3" colwidth="4*"/>
                    <thead>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Class Name</entry>
                            <entry>Value Type</entry>
                            <entry>Interpretation</entry>
                        </row>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry><classname>BooleanGuacamoleProperty</classname></entry>
                            <entry><classname>Boolean</classname></entry>
                            <entry>The values "true" and "false" are parsed as their corresponding
                                    <classname>Boolean</classname> values. Any other value results
                                in a parse error.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><classname>IntegerGuacamoleProperty</classname></entry>
                            <entry><classname>Integer</classname></entry>
                            <entry>Numeric strings are parsed as <classname>Integer</classname>
                                values. Non-numeric strings will result in a parse error.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><classname>LongGuacamoleProperty</classname></entry>
                            <entry><classname>Long</classname></entry>
                            <entry>Numeric strings are parsed as <classname>Long</classname> values.
                                Non-numeric strings will result in a parse error.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><classname>StringGuacamoleProperty</classname></entry>
                            <entry><classname>String</classname></entry>
                            <entry>The property value is returned as an untouched
                                    <classname>String</classname>. No parsing is performed, and
                                parse errors cannot occur.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><classname>FileGuacamoleProperty</classname></entry>
                            <entry><classname>File</classname></entry>
                            <entry>The property is interpreted as a filename, and a new
                                    <classname>File</classname> pointing to that filename is
                                returned. If the filename is invalid, a parse error will be thrown.
                                Note that the file need not exist or be accessible for the filename
                                to be valid.</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </informaltable>
            <para>To use these types, you must extend the base class, implementing the
                    <methodname>getName()</methodname> function to identify your property.
                Typically, you would declare these properties as static members of some class
                containing all properties relevant to your extension:</para>
            <informalexample>
                <programlisting>public class MyProperties {

    public static <replaceable>MY_PROPERTY</replaceable> = new IntegerGuacamoleProperty() {

        @Override
        public String getName() { return "<replaceable>my-property</replaceable>"; }

    };

}</programlisting>
            </informalexample>
            <para>Your property can then be retrieved with <methodname>getProperty()</methodname> or
                    <methodname>getRequiredProperty()</methodname>:</para>
            <informalexample>
                <programlisting>Integer value = environment.getProperty(<replaceable>MyProperties.MY_PROPERTY</replaceable>);</programlisting>
            </informalexample>
            <para>If you need more sophisticated parsing, you can also implement your own property
                types by implementing the <classname>GuacamoleProperty</classname> interface. The
                only functions to implement are <methodname>getName()</methodname>, which returns
                the name of the property, and <methodname>parseValue()</methodname>, which parses a
                given string and returns its value.</para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="advanced-config">
            <title>Advanced configuration</title>
            <para>If you need more structured data than provided by simple properties, you can place
                completely arbitrary files in a hierarchy of your choosing anywhere within
                    <varname>GUACAMOLE_HOME</varname> as long as you avoid placing your files in
                directories reserved for other purposes as described above.</para>
            <para>The Environment interface exposes the location of
                    <varname>GUACAMOLE_HOME</varname> through the
                    <methodname>getGuacamoleHome()</methodname> function. This function returns a
                standard Java <classname>File</classname> which can then be used to locate other
                files or directories within <varname>GUACAMOLE_HOME</varname>:</para>
            <informalexample>
                <programlisting>File myConfigFile = new File(environment.getGuacamoleHome(), "my-config.xml");</programlisting>
                <para>There is no guarantee that <varname>GUACAMOLE_HOME</varname> or your file will
                    exist, and you should verify this before proceeding further in your extension's
                    configuration process, but once this is done you can simply parse your file as
                    you see fit.</para>
            </informalexample>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="auth-providers">
        <title>Authentication providers</title>
        <para>The main use of guacamole-ext is to provide custom authentication
            for Guacamole through the implementation of authentication
            providers. An authentication provider is any class which implements
            the <classname>AuthenticationProvider</classname> interface,
            implementing the only function defined by that interface:
                <methodname>getUserContext()</methodname>. This function is
            required to return a "context" which provides access to only those
            users and configurations accessible with the given credentials, and
            enforces its own security model.</para>
        <para>The credentials given are abstract and while Guacamole the web
            application implements a username/password driven login screen, you
            are not required to user usernames and passwords; the
                <classname>Credentials</classname> class given to the
            authentication provider provides access to all HTTP parameters in
            general, as well as cookies and SSL information.</para>
        <para>The Guacamole web application includes a basic authentication
            provider implementation which parses an XML file to determine which
            users exist, their corresponding passwords, and what configurations
            those users have access to. This is the part of Guacamole that reads
            the <filename>user-mapping.xml</filename> file. If you use a custom
            authentication provider for your authentication, this file will
            probably not be required.</para>
        <para>The community has implemented authentication providers which
            access databases, use LDAP, or even perform no authentication at
            all, redirecting all users to a single configuration specified in
                <filename>guacamole.properties</filename>.</para>
        <para>A minimal authentication provider is implemented in the tutorials
            later, and the upstream authentication provider implemented within
            Guacamole, as well as the authentication providers implemented by
            the community, are good examples for how authentication can be
            extended without having to implement a whole new web
            application.</para>
        <section>
            <title><classname>SimpleAuthenticationProvider</classname></title>
            <para>The <classname>SimpleAuthenticationProvider</classname> class
                provides a much simpler means of implementing authentication
                when you do not require the ability to add and remove users and
                connections. It is an abstract class and requires only one
                function implementation:
                    <methodname>getAuthorizedConfigurations()</methodname>.</para>
            <para>This function is required to return a
                    <classname>Map</classname> of unique IDs to configurations,
                where these configurations are all configurations accessible
                with the provided credentials. As before, the credentials given
                are abstract. You are not required to use usernames and
                passwords.</para>
            <para>The configurations referred to by the function name are
                instances of <classname>GuacamoleConfiguration</classname> (part
                of guacamole-common), which is just a wrapper around a protocol
                name and set of parameter name/value pairs. The name of the
                protocol to use and a set of parameters is the minimum
                information required for other parts of the Guacamole API to
                complete the handshake required by the Guacamole
                protocol.</para>
            <para>When a class that extends
                    <classname>SimpleAuthenticationProvider</classname> is asked
                for more advanced operations by the web application,
                    <classname>SimpleAuthenticationProvider</classname> simply
                returns that there is no permission to do so. This effectively
                disables all administrative functionality within the web
                interface.</para>
            <para>If you choose to go the simple route, most of the rest of this
                chapter is irrelevant. Permissions, security model, and various
                classes will be discussed that are all handled for you
                automatically by
                    <classname>SimpleAuthenticationProvider</classname>.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>The <classname>UserContext</classname></title>
            <para>The <classname>UserContext</classname> is the root of all
                operations. It is used to list, create, modify, or delete users
                and connections, as well as to query available
                permissions.</para>
            <para>The Guacamole web application uses permissions queries against
                the <classname>UserContext</classname> to determine what
                operations to present, but <emphasis>beware that it is up to the
                        <classname>UserContext</classname> to actually enforce
                    these restrictions</emphasis>. The Guacamole web application
                will not enforce restrictions on behalf of the
                    <classname>UserContext</classname>.</para>
            <para>The <classname>UserContext</classname> is the sole means of
                entry and the sole means of modification available to a
                logged-in user. If the <classname>UserContext</classname>
                refuses to perform an operation (by throwing an exception), the
                user cannot perform the operation at all.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title><classname>Directory</classname> classes</title>
            <para>Access to users and connections is given through
                    <classname>Directory</classname> classes. These
                    <classname>Directory</classname> classes are similar to Java
                collections, but they also embody object update semantics.
                Objects can be retrieved from a <classname>Directory</classname>
                using its <methodname>get()</methodname> function and added or
                removed with <methodname>add()</methodname> and
                    <methodname>remove()</methodname> respectively, but objects
                already in the set can also be updated by passing an updated
                object to its <methodname>update()</methodname> function.</para>
            <para>An implementation of a <classname>Directory</classname> can
                rely on these functions to define the semantics surrounding all
                operations. The <methodname>add()</methodname> function is
                called only when creating new objects, the
                    <methodname>update()</methodname> function is called only
                when updating an object previously retrieved with
                    <methodname>get()</methodname>, and
                    <methodname>remove()</methodname> is called only when
                removing an existing object by its identifier.</para>
            <para>When implementing an
                    <classname>AuthenticationProvider</classname>, you must
                ensure that the <classname>UserContext</classname> will only
                return <classname>Directory</classname> classes that
                automatically enforce the permissions associated with all
                objects and the associated user.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Permissions</title>
            <para>The permissions system within guacamole-ext is an advisory system. It is the means
                by which an authentication module describes to the web application what a user is
                allowed to do. The body of permissions granted to a user describes which objects
                that user can see and what they can do to those objects, and thus suggests how the
                Guacamole interface should appear to that user.</para>
            <para><emphasis>Permissions are not the means by which access is restricted</emphasis>;
                they are purely a means of describing access level. An implementation may internally
                use the permission objects to define restrictions, but this is not required. It is
                up to the implementation to enforce its own restrictions by throwing exceptions when
                an operation is not allowed, and to correctly communicate the abilities of
                individual users through these permissions.</para>
            <section>
                <title>System permissions</title>
                <para>System permissions describe access to operations that manipulate the system as
                    a whole, rather than specific objects. This includes the creation of new
                    objects, as object creation directly affects the system, and per-object controls
                    cannot exist before the object is actually created.</para>
                <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><constant>ADMINISTER</constant></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>The user is a super-user - the Guacamole equivalent of root. They
                                are allowed to manipulate of system-level permissions and all other
                                objects. This permission implies all others.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><constant>CREATE_CONNECTION</constant></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>The user is allowed to create new connections. If a user has this
                                permission, the management interface will display components related
                                to connection creation.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><constant>CREATE_CONNECTION_GROUP</constant></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>The user is allowed to create new connection groups. If a user has
                                this permission, the management interface will display components
                                related to connection group creation.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><constant>CREATE_SHARING_PROFILE</constant></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>The user is allowed to create new sharing profiles. If a user has
                                this permission, the management interface will display components
                                related to sharing profile creation.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><constant>CREATE_USER</constant></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>The user is allowed to create other users. If a user has this
                                permission, the management interface will display components related
                                to user creation.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Object permissions</title>
                <para>Object permissions describe access to operations that affect a particular
                    object. Guacamole currently defines four types of objects which can be
                    associated with permissions: users, connections, connection groups, and sharing
                    profiles. Each object permission associates a single user with an action that
                    may be performed on a single object.</para>
                <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><constant>ADMINISTER</constant></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>The user may grant or revoke permissions involving this object.
                                "Involving", in this case, refers to either side of the permission
                                association, and includes both the user to whom the permission is
                                granted and the object the permission affects.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><constant>DELETE</constant></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>The user may delete this object. This is distinct from the
                                    <constant>ADMINISTER</constant> permission which deals only with
                                permissions. A user with this permission will see the "Delete"
                                button when applicable.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><constant>READ</constant></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>The user may see that this object exists and read the properties
                                of that object.</para>
                            <para>Note that the implementation is <emphasis>not required to divulge
                                    the true underlying properties of any object</emphasis>. The
                                parameters of a connection or sharing profile, the type or contents
                                of a connection group, the password of a user, etc. all need not be
                                exposed.</para>
                            <para>This is particularly important from the perspective of security
                                when it comes to connections, as the parameters of a connection are
                                only truly needed when a connection is being modified, and likely
                                should not be exposed otherwise. The actual connection operation is
                                always performed internally by the authentication provider, and thus
                                does not require client-side knowledge of anything beyond the
                                connection's existence.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><constant>UPDATE</constant></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>The user may change the properties of this object.</para>
                            <para>In the case of users, this means the user's password can be
                                altered. <emphasis>Permissions are not considered properties of a
                                    user</emphasis>, nor objects in their own right, but rather
                                associations between a user and an action which may involve another
                                object.</para>
                            <para>The properties of a connection include its name, protocol, parent
                                connection group, and parameters. The properties of a connection
                                group include its name, type, parent connection group, and children.
                                The properties of a sharing profile include its name, primary
                                connection, and parameters.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Connections and history</title>
            <para>Authentication modules must return <classname>Connection</classname> objects which
                each implement a <methodname>connect()</methodname> function. When this function is
                called, the connection must be made if permission is available.</para>
            <para>This new separation of concerns makes more sense when you
                consider that as connecting is an operation on a
                    <classname>Connection</classname>, access to performing that
                operation must be restricted through the
                    <classname>AuthenticationProvider</classname>, and thus must
                be enforced within the
                    <classname>AuthenticationProvider</classname>. This
                separation also opens the door for things like load balancing of
                connections and restricting concurrent access to
                connections.</para>
            <para>When a connection is made or terminated, it is also the duty
                of the authentication module to maintain the connection history.
                Each connection has a corresponding list of
                    <classname>ConnectionRecord</classname> objects, each of
                which is associated with a past connection or a currently-active
                connection. This information will ultimately be exposed to the
                user as a history list when they view a connection in the
                management interface or as a simple active user count on the
                connection, advising the user of existing activity.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
</chapter>
