<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xml:id="guacamole-ext" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    version="5.0" xml:lang="en" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <title>guacamole-ext</title>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>API</primary>
        <secondary>Java</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>guacamole-ext</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>While not strictly part of the Java API provided by the Guacamole
        project, guacamole-ext is a subset of the API used by the Guacamole web
        application, exposed within a separate project such that extensions,
        specifically authentication providers, can be written to tweak Guacamole
        to fit well in existing deployments.</para>
    <section>
        <title>Common configuration</title>
        <para>For the sake of ease of development and providing a common
            location for configuration of both Guacamole and its extensions,
            guacamole-ext provides utility classes for accessing the main
            configuration file, <filename>guacamole.properties</filename>, and
            for accessing the main root directory for housing configuration
            files: <varname>GUACAMOLE_HOME</varname>.</para>
        <section>
            <title><classname>GuacamoleProperties</classname></title>
            <para><classname>GuacamoleProperties</classname> is a utility class
                for accessing the properties declared within
                    <filename>guacamole.properties</filename>. Each property is
                typesafe and handles its own parsing - retrieving a property is
                as simple as calling <methodname>getProperty()</methodname> or
                    <methodname>getRequiredProperty()</methodname>.</para>
            <para>Because of this ease-of-access to guacamole.properties within
                Guacamole and all extensions, the
                    <filename>guacamole.properties</filename> file is an ideal
                place to store unstructured, extension-specific configuration
                information.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title><classname>GuacamoleHome</classname></title>
            <para>If you need more structured data than provided by simple
                properties, placing XML or some other separate file within
                    <varname>GUACAMOLE_HOME</varname> (or a subdirectory
                thereof) is a decent way to achieve this. The
                    <classname>GuacamoleHome</classname> class provides access
                to the <varname>GUACAMOLE_HOME</varname> directory, abstracting
                away the decision process that determines which directory is
                considered <varname>GUACAMOLE_HOME</varname>.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="auth-providers">
        <title>Authentication providers</title>
        <para>The main use of guacamole-ext is to provide custom authentication
            for Guacamole through the implementation of authentication
            providers. An authentication provider is any class which implements
            the <classname>AuthenticationProvider</classname> interface,
            implementing the only function defined by that interface:
                <methodname>getUserContext()</methodname>. This function is
            required to return a "context" which provides access to only those
            users and configurations accessible with the given credentials, and
            enforces its own security model.</para>
        <para>The credentials given are abstract and while Guacamole the web
            application implements a username/password driven login screen, you
            are not required to user usernames and passwords; the
                <classname>Credentials</classname> class given to the
            authentication provider provides access to all HTTP parameters in
            general, as well as cookies and SSL information.</para>
        <para>The Guacamole web application includes a basic authentication
            provider implementation which parses an XML file to determine which
            users exist, their corresponding passwords, and what configurations
            those users have access to. This is the part of Guacamole that reads
            the <filename>user-mapping.xml</filename> file. If you use a custom
            authentication provider for your authentication, this file will
            probably not be required.</para>
        <para>The community has implemented authentication providers which
            access databases, use LDAP, or even perform no authentication at
            all, redirecting all users to a single configuration specified in
                <filename>guacamole.properties</filename>.</para>
        <para>A minimal authentication provider is implemented in the tutorials
            later, and the upstream authentication provider implemented within
            Guacamole, as well as the authentication providers implemented by
            the community, are good examples for how authentication can be
            extended without having to implement a whole new web
            application.</para>
        <section>
            <title><classname>SimpleAuthenticationProvider</classname></title>
            <para>The <classname>SimpleAuthenticationProvider</classname> class
                provides a much simpler means of implementing authentication
                when you do not require the ability to add and remove users and
                connections. It is an abstract class and requires only one
                function implementation:
                    <methodname>getAuthorizedConfigurations()</methodname>.</para>
            <para>This function is required to return a
                    <classname>Map</classname> of unique IDs to configurations,
                where these configurations are all configurations accessible
                with the provided credentials. As before, the credentials given
                are abstract. You are not required to use usernames and
                passwords.</para>
            <para>The configurations referred to by the function name are
                instances of <classname>GuacamoleConfiguration</classname> (part
                of guacamole-common), which is just a wrapper around a protocol
                name and set of parameter name/value pairs. The name of the
                protocol to use and a set of parameters is the minimum
                information required for other parts of the Guacamole API to
                complete the handshake required by the Guacamole
                protocol.</para>
            <para>When a class that extends
                    <classname>SimpleAuthenticationProvider</classname> is asked
                for more advanced operations by the web application,
                    <classname>SimpleAuthenticationProvider</classname> simply
                returns that there is no permission to do so. This effectively
                disables all administrative functionality within the web
                interface.</para>
            <para>If you choose to go the simple route, most of the rest of this
                chapter is irrelevant. Permissions, security model, and various
                classes will be discussed that are all handled for you
                automatically by
                    <classname>SimpleAuthenticationProvider</classname>.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>The <classname>UserContext</classname></title>
            <para>The <classname>UserContext</classname> is the root of all
                operations. It is used to list, create, modify, or delete users
                and connections, as well as to query available
                permissions.</para>
            <para>The Guacamole web application uses permissions queries against
                the <classname>UserContext</classname> to determine what
                operations to present, but <emphasis>beware that it is up to the
                        <classname>UserContext</classname> to actually enforce
                    these restrictions</emphasis>. The Guacamole web application
                will not enforce restrictions on behalf of the
                    <classname>UserContext</classname>.</para>
            <para>The <classname>UserContext</classname> is the sole means of
                entry and the sole means of modification available to a
                logged-in user. If the <classname>UserContext</classname>
                refuses to perform an operation (by throwing an exception), the
                user cannot perform the operation at all.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title><classname>Directory</classname> classes</title>
            <para>Access to users and connections is given through
                    <classname>Directory</classname> classes. These
                    <classname>Directory</classname> classes are similar to Java
                collections, but they also embody object update semantics.
                Objects can be retrieved from a <classname>Directory</classname>
                using its <methodname>get()</methodname> function and added or
                removed with <methodname>add()</methodname> and
                    <methodname>remove()</methodname> respectively, but objects
                already in the set can also be updated by passing an updated
                object to its <methodname>update()</methodname> function.</para>
            <para>An implementation of a <classname>Directory</classname> can
                rely on these functions to define the semantics surrounding all
                operations. The <methodname>add()</methodname> function is
                called only when creating new objects, the
                    <methodname>update()</methodname> function is called only
                when updating an object previously retrieved with
                    <methodname>get()</methodname>, and
                    <methodname>remove()</methodname> is called only when
                removing an existing object by its identifier.</para>
            <para>When implementing an
                    <classname>AuthenticationProvider</classname>, you must
                ensure that the <classname>UserContext</classname> will only
                return <classname>Directory</classname> classes that
                automatically enforce the permissions associated with all
                objects and the associated user.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Permissions</title>
            <para>The permissions system within guacamole-ext is the means with
                which an authentication module communicates with the web
                application, informing it of what the user is allowed to do. The
                presence or lack of permissions for certain operations dictates
                how the web interface displays itself: whether the "Manage"
                button is displayed, whether the user or connection management
                sections (or both) are displayed, etc.</para>
            <para><emphasis>Permissions are not the means through which access
                    is restricted</emphasis>. An implementation may use the
                permission objects to define restrictions, but this is not
                required. It is up to the implementation to enforce its own
                restrictions by throwing exceptions when an operation is not
                allowed.</para>
            <section>
                <title>System permissions</title>
                <para>System permissions grant access to operations that
                    manipulate the system as a whole, rather than specific
                    objects. This includes the creation of new objects, as
                    object creation directly affects the system, and per-object
                    controls cannot exist before the object is actually
                    created.</para>
                <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><type>ADMINISTER</type></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Allows manipulation of system-level
                                permissions. The semantics of the system-level
                                    <type>ADMINISTER</type> permission are up to
                                the implementor of the authentication module,
                                but in general this permission implies all other
                                permissions. A user having this permission can
                                implicitly create and manage any object.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><type>CREATE_CONNECTION</type></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Allows creation of new connections. If a user has this permission,
                                they will see the connection management interface and the "Manage"
                                button. Within this interface, they will be able to create new
                                connections.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><type>CREATE_CONNECTION_GROUP</type></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Allows creation of new connections groups. If a user has this
                                permission, they will see the connection management interface and
                                the "Manage" button. Within this interface, they will be able to
                                create new connection groups.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><type>CREATE_USER</type></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Allows creation of new users. If a user has
                                this permission, they will see the user
                                management interface and the "Manage"
                                button.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>User permissions</title>
                <para>User permissions grant access to operations that affect a
                    specific user. Each user permission has a definite and
                    single associated user that is the object of the
                    operation.</para>
                <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><type>ADMINISTER</type></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Allows changing visibility of the user. A user
                                with <type>ADMINISTER</type> permission on
                                another user can add and remove permissions
                                related to that user. Note that adding or
                                removing permissions on a user implicitly
                                requires <type>UPDATE</type> permission on that
                                user.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><type>DELETE</type></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Allows deletion of the associated user. This
                                is distinct from the <type>ADMINISTER</type>
                                permission which deals only with modification to
                                the permissions associated with a user. A user
                                with this permission will see the "Delete"
                                button when editing the corresponding
                                user.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><type>READ</type></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Allows the user to be read. A particular user
                                will not appear in the user management section
                                unless the user viewing it has <type>READ</type>
                                permission on that specific user.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><type>UPDATE</type></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Allows the user to be updated. This means altering the user's
                                password or adding or removing permissions from that user. Note the
                                difference between <type>UPDATE</type> and <type>ADMINISTER</type>:
                                the <type>UPDATE</type> permission allows the permissions
                                    <emphasis>of</emphasis> a user to be changed, while
                                    <type>ADMINISTER</type> permission allows permissions
                                    <emphasis>relating to</emphasis> a user to be changed. A user
                                with this permission will see the "Manage" button.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Connection permissions</title>
                <para>Connection permissions grant access to operations that
                    affect a specific connection. Each connection permission has
                    a definite and single associated connection that is the
                    object of the operation. The semantics of each operation
                    differ slightly from the similar user permissions, but the
                    general principles behind them are the same.</para>
                <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><type>ADMINISTER</type></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Allows changing visibility of the connection. A user with
                                    <type>ADMINISTER</type> permission on a connection can add and
                                remove permissions related to that connection, and will see the
                                "Manage" button.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><type>DELETE</type></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Allows deletion of the associated connection.
                                This is distinct from the
                                    <type>ADMINISTER</type> permission which
                                deals only with modification to the permissions
                                associated with a connection. A user with this
                                permission will see the "Delete" button when
                                editing the corresponding connection.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><type>READ</type></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Allows the connection to be read. A particular connection will not
                                appear in the connection list nor in the connection management
                                section unless the user viewing it has <type>READ</type> permission
                                on that specific connection. <type>READ</type> permission is
                                required for a user to have permission to actually use a connection,
                                unless that connection is part of a balancing connection group for
                                which the user has <type>READ</type> permission.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><type>UPDATE</type></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Allows the connection to be updated. This means editing the
                                connection's parameters or changing the connection's protocol. A
                                user with this permission will see the "Manage" button.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Connection group permissions</title>
                <para>Connection group permissions grant access to operations that affect a specific
                    connection group. Connection group permissions are extremely similar to
                    connection permissions, with some minor differences.</para>
                <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><type>ADMINISTER</type></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Allows changing visibility of the connection group. A user with
                                    <type>ADMINISTER</type> permission on a connection group can add
                                and remove permissions related to that connection group, and will
                                see the "Manage" button. Users with <type>ADMINISTER</type>
                                permission on a balancing connection group can see the contents of
                                that group. To users without <type>ADMINISTER</type> permission, a
                                balancing group looks like a connection.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><type>DELETE</type></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Allows deletion of the associated connection group. This is
                                distinct from the <type>ADMINISTER</type> permission which deals
                                only with modification to the permissions associated with a
                                connection group. A user with this permission will see the "Delete"
                                button when editing the corresponding connection group.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><type>READ</type></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Allows the connection group to be read. A particular connection
                                group will not appear in the connection list nor in the connection
                                management section unless the user viewing it has <type>READ</type>
                                permission on that specific connection group. <type>READ</type>
                                permission is required for a user to have permission to actually use
                                a connection.</para>
                            <para>A user with <type>READ</type> permission on a group will also be
                                able to see any contained connections or groups for which they also
                                have <type>READ</type> permission. <type>READ</type> permission is
                                not sufficient to see the contents of a balancing group.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><type>UPDATE</type></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Allows the connection group to be updated. This means editing the
                                connection group's name, type, or contents. A user with this
                                permission will see the "Manage" button.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Connections and history</title>
            <para>Authentication modules must return <classname>Connection</classname> objects which
                each implement a <methodname>connect()</methodname> function. When this function is
                called, the connection must be made if permission is available.</para>
            <para>This new separation of concerns makes more sense when you
                consider that as connecting is an operation on a
                    <classname>Connection</classname>, access to performing that
                operation must be restricted through the
                    <classname>AuthenticationProvider</classname>, and thus must
                be enforced within the
                    <classname>AuthenticationProvider</classname>. This
                separation also opens the door for things like load balancing of
                connections and restricting concurrent access to
                connections.</para>
            <para>When a connection is made or terminated, it is also the duty
                of the authentication module to maintain the connection history.
                Each connection has a corresponding list of
                    <classname>ConnectionRecord</classname> objects, each of
                which is associated with a past connection or a currently-active
                connection. This information will ultimately be exposed to the
                user as a history list when they view a connection in the
                management interface or as a simple active user count on the
                connection, advising the user of existing activity.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="event-listeners">
        <title>Event listeners</title>
        <para>Although not used internally by the web application, the web
            application provides an event system which can be hooked into with
            listener objects, such that a class within the classpath of
            Guacamole can receive events when something noteworthy happens in
            the application layer, and take some sort of action.</para>
        <para>Currently, the web application provides events for when the tunnel
            is opened or closed, and when an authentication attempt succeeds or
            fails. In most cases, the class listening for these events can also
            cancel whatever action just occurred.</para>
        <section xml:id="tunnel-connect-listener">
            <title><classname>TunnelConnectListener</classname></title>
            <para>When a tunnel is connected to by the JavaScript client,
                Guacamole informs all installed instances of
                    <classname>TunnelConnectListener</classname> by calling
                their <methodname>tunnelConnected()</methodname> function with a
                new <classname>TunnelConnectEvent</classname>, which contains
                the tunnel that was just connected, as well as any associated
                credentials. If <methodname>tunnelConnected()</methodname>
                returns <constant>false</constant>, the connect attempt will be
                overridden and denied.</para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="tunnel-close-listener">
            <title><classname>TunnelCloseListener</classname></title>
            <para>When a tunnel is connected to by the JavaScript client,
                Guacamole informs all installed instances of
                    <classname>TunnelCloseListener</classname> by calling their
                    <methodname>tunnelClosed()</methodname> function with a new
                    <classname>TunnelCloseEvent</classname>, which contains the
                tunnel that is about to be closed, as well as any associated
                credentials. If <methodname>tunnelClosed()</methodname> returns
                    <constant>false</constant>, the attempt close the tunnel
                will be overridden and denied, and the tunnel will remain
                open.</para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="authentication-success-listener">
            <title><classname>AuthenticationSuccessListener</classname></title>
            <para>If a user successfully authenticates with the web application,
                Guacamole informs all installed instances of
                    <classname>AuthenticationSuccessListener</classname> by
                calling their <methodname>authenticationSucceeded()</methodname>
                function with a new
                    <classname>AuthenticationSuccessEvent</classname> which
                contains the credentials used. The implementation of this
                function has the opportunity to cancel the authentication
                attempt, effectively denying access despite being otherwise
                valid, by returning <constant>false</constant>.</para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="authentication-failure-listener">
            <title><classname>AuthenticationFailureListener</classname></title>
            <para>If a user fails to authenticate with the web application,
                Guacamole informs all installed instances of
                    <classname>AuthenticationFailureListener</classname> by
                calling their <methodname>authenticationFailed()</methodname>
                function with a new
                    <classname>AuthenticationFailureEvent</classname> which
                contains the credentials used. Unlike other listeners, this
                event cannot be canceled by returning
                <constant>false</constant>. All failed authentication attempts
                "succeed" in failing, and an implementation of
                    <classname>AuthenticationFailureListener</classname> cannot
                force an authentication attempt to succeed by denying that
                failure.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
</chapter>
