<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xml:id="installing-guacamole" 
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="en"
    xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

    <title>Installing Guacamole</title>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>Guacamole</primary>
        <secondary>installing</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <!--
    - From packages 
    -->

    <section xml:id="binary-packages">

        <title>Pre-built packages</title>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>packages</primary>
            <secondary>pre-built</secondary>
        </indexterm>

        <para>By far, the easiest way to install Guacamole is through pre-built
            binary packages. Binary packages are provided with every Guacamole
            release for several Linux distributions, and there may be Guacamole
            packages available in the official repository of your
            distribution.</para>

        <para>If your distribution provides Guacamole packages for you, this is
            the preferred method of installing Guacamole. Install your
            distribution's Guacamole package, and then follow the common
            instructions here for configuring Guacamole once it is
            installed.</para>

        <para>If your distribution does not provide Guacamole packages, or the
            packages provided are too old, you can try the packages built by the
            Guacamole project with every release. If the Guacamole project does
            not provide packages for your specific distribution, you will need
            to build everything yourself from source.</para>
        <important>
            <para>Be aware that Guacamole is a remote desktop gateway, and
                cannot access your desktop's display without a remote desktop
                server of some kind to connect to. Guacamole does not contain
                its own VNC or RDP server, and these installation procedures
                will not walk you through the installation of a VNC or RDP
                server.</para>
            <para>Your distribution of choice will provide documentation for
                setting up VNC, as will the documentation provided by those that
                created the VNC server you wish to use. If you are going to use
                RDP to connect to Windows computers, Microsoft (and many others
                on the internet) provides documentation describing how to set up
                remote desktop.</para>
        </important>

        <section xml:id="linux-support">

            <title>Supported distribution versions</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>Linux</primary>
                <secondary>supported versions</secondary>
            </indexterm>

            <para>The Guacamole project supports all stable versions of Debian,
                Ubuntu, and Fedora which have not reached end-of-life. The only
                exception to this is when a particular version cannot be
                supported because the upstream repository is missing a critical
                dependency, in which case some or all of the packages built by
                the Guacamole project will not be available for that
                distribution. </para>

            <para>Packages for all supported versions of Linux distributions are
                available from the <link xl:href="http://guac-dev.org/"
                    >Guacamole web site</link>. <indexterm>
                    <primary>Guacamole</primary>
                    <secondary>downloading</secondary>
                </indexterm></para>

        </section>

        <section xml:id="binary-dependencies">

            <title>Installing dependencies</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>Guacamole</primary>
                <secondary>dependencies</secondary>
            </indexterm>

            <para>Different components of Guacamole depend on different packages
                provided by your distribution in order to function. </para>

            <para>The Guacamole web application depends on a servlet container
                like Apache Tomcat. This guide assumes you are using Apache
                Tomcat as your servlet container, but others will work as well.
                You will need to consult the documentation of your chosen
                servlet container for any details regarding installation of web
                applications. </para>

            <para><indexterm>
                    <primary>Guacamole</primary>
                    <secondary>dependencies</secondary>
                    <tertiary>Debian</tertiary>
                </indexterm><indexterm>
                    <primary>Guacamole</primary>
                    <secondary>dependencies</secondary>
                    <tertiary>Ubuntu</tertiary>
                </indexterm>For Debian and Ubuntu, Apache Tomcat is provided by
                the <package>tomcat6</package> package, while the VNC library
                required for VNC support is provided by
                    <package>libvncserver0</package>, and RDP support is
                provided by <package>libfreerdp1</package>. </para>

            <example>
                <title>Installing Guacamole dependencies on Debian or Ubuntu</title>
                <screen><prompt>$</prompt> sudo  apt-get install tomcat6 libvncserver0 libfreerdp1</screen>
            </example>

            <para>
                <indexterm>
                    <primary>Guacamole</primary>
                    <secondary>dependencies</secondary>
                    <tertiary>Fedora</tertiary>
                </indexterm>
                The Apache Tomcat package for Fedora is also called
                <package>tomcat6</package>. VNC support is provided by
                <package>libvncserver</package>, and RDP support is provided by
                <package>freerdp</package>.
            </para>

            <example>
                <title>Installing Guacamole dependencies on Fedora</title>
                <screen><prompt>$</prompt> su
<prompt>Password:</prompt> <replaceable>password</replaceable>
<prompt>#</prompt> yum install tomcat6 libvncserver freerdp</screen>
            </example>

        </section>

        <section xml:id="installing-guacamole-packages">
            
            <title>Installing Guacamole packages</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>Guacamole</primary>
                <secondary>packages</secondary>
                <tertiary>installing</tertiary>
            </indexterm>

            <para>
                Once dependencies are installed, the official Guacamole
                packages can be installed.  Guacamole is split into multiple
                packages, one package providing the web application, others
                providing the native components (proxy daemon and library) or
                support for specific protocols (VNC and RDP).
            </para>

            <para>
                The easiest way to obtain all packages in one fell swoop is to
                download the "bundle" archive of the latest release from the
                <link xl:href="http://guac-dev.org/">Guacamole web site</link>.
                <indexterm>
                    <primary>Guacamole</primary>
                    <secondary>downloading</secondary>
                    <tertiary>bundles</tertiary>
                </indexterm>
            </para>

            <example>
                <title>Installing Guacamole packages on Debian or Ubuntu</title>
<screen><prompt>$</prompt> tar -xzf guacamole-0.6.2-ubuntu-12.04-amd64.tar.gz
<prompt>$</prompt> cd guacamole-0.6.2-ubuntu-12.04-amd64/
<prompt>$</prompt> ls
<computeroutput>guacamole_0.6.1-1_all.deb
guacamole-tomcat_0.6.1-1_all.deb
guacd_0.6.1-1_amd64.deb
libguac3_0.6.2-1_amd64.deb
libguac-client-rdp0_0.6.1-1_amd64.deb
libguac-client-vnc0_0.6.0-1_amd64.deb
libguac-dev_0.6.2-1_amd64.deb</computeroutput>
<prompt>$</prompt> sudo dpkg -i *.deb</screen>
            </example>

            <example>
                <title>Installing Guacamole packages on Fedora</title>
<screen><prompt>$</prompt> tar -xzf guacamole-0.6.2-fedora-17-x86_64.tar.gz
<prompt>$</prompt> cd guacamole-0.6.2-fedora-17-x86_64/
<prompt>$</prompt> ls
<computeroutput>guacamole-0.6.1-1.noarch.rpm
guacd-0.6.1-1.x86_64.rpm
libguac3-0.6.2-1.x86_64.rpm
libguac-client-vnc0-0.6.0-1.x86_64.rpm
libguac3-devel-0.6.2-1.x86_64.rpm
libguac-client-rdp-0.6.1-1.x86_64.rpm</computeroutput>
<prompt>$</prompt> su
<prompt>Password:</prompt> <replaceable>password</replaceable>
<prompt>#</prompt> rpm -i *.rpm</screen>
            </example>

        </section>

    </section>

    <!--
    - From source
    -->

    <section xml:id="building-guacamole-from-source">
        <title>Building Guacamole from source</title>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>compiling</primary>
            <secondary>Guacamole</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>Guacamole</primary>
            <secondary>compiling</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>Building the components of Guacamole from source is not difficult,
            providing you have the necessary tools installed already. The source
            for the entirety of Guacamole is available from the Guacamole
            project web site in convenient source archives, each named after the
            component they contain. Each archive also contains a file named
                <filename>README</filename> which lists detailed instructions
            for building and installing. </para>
        <para>To compile the C components, you will need a C compiler (such as
            gcc) and the libraries that each component depends on. Note that
            many Linux distribution separates library packages into binary and
            "development" packages; you will need to install the development
            packages. These will usually end in a "-dev" or "-devel" suffix. </para>
        <section xml:id="compiling-libguac">
            <title>Compiling libguac</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>compiling</primary>
                <secondary>libguac</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>libguac</primary>
                <secondary>compiling</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>The core Guacamole C library, libguac, is a common dependency
                of all native components of Guacamole. It depends on Cairo, a
                graphics library, and libpng, the official PNG library. Once you
                have installed these dependencies, building libguac is
                easy:</para>
            <example>
                <title>Building libguac from source</title>
                <screen><prompt>$</prompt> tar -xzf libguac-0.6.2.tar.gz
<prompt>$</prompt> cd libguac-0.6.2/
<prompt>$</prompt> ./configure
<prompt>$</prompt> make
<prompt>$</prompt> sudo make install
<prompt>$</prompt> sudo ldconfig               </screen>
            </example>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="compiling-guacd">
            <title>Compiling guacd</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>compiling</primary>
                <secondary>guacd</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>guacd</primary>
                <secondary>compiling</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>Once libguac is compiled and installed, guacd and protocol
                support plugins can be compiled and installed as well. None of
                these components can be compiled or installed until after
                libguac as they all depend on it heavily.</para>
            <para>guacd is the proxy daemon that runs on your Guacamole server,
                accepting connections from the Guacamole web application on
                behalf of remote users. It effectively translates between common
                remote desktop protocols like VNC or RDP by dynamically loading
                protocol support plugins. Building guacd creates an executable
                called <filename>guacd</filename> which can be run manually or,
                if you wish, automatically when your computer starts up.</para>
            <example>
                <title>Building guacd from source</title>
                <screen><prompt>$</prompt> tar -xzf guacd-0.6.1.tar.gz
<prompt>$</prompt> cd guacd-0.6.1/
<prompt>$</prompt> ./configure --with-init-dir=/etc/init.d
<prompt>$</prompt> make
<prompt>$</prompt> sudo make install             </screen>
            </example>
            <para>
                <indexterm>
                    <primary>guacd</primary>
                    <secondary>startup script</secondary>
                </indexterm> If you do not wish guacd to start automatically at
                boot, leave off the <option>--with-init-dir=/etc/init.d</option>
                option. If the directory containing your distribution's startup
                scripts differs from the common
                <filename>/etc/init.d</filename>, replace
                    <filename>/etc/init.d</filename> with the proper directory
                here. You may need to consult your distribution's documentation,
                or do a little digging in <filename>/etc</filename>, to
                determine the proper location. </para>
            <para>Even after installing guacd and its startup script, you will
                likely still have to activate the service for it to start
                automatically. Doing this varies by distribution, but each
                distribution will have documentation describing how to do so.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="compiling-libguac-client-vnc">
            <title>VNC support</title>
            <para>All protocol support in Guacamole is modular, even VNC, the
                first protocol supported by Guacamole and the protocol provided
                by default in all Guacamole installations. </para>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>compiling</primary>
                <secondary>VNC support</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>VNC support</primary>
                <secondary>compiling</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <para> Building the VNC support plugin, libguac-client-vnc, requires
                libvncclient, which is part of libvncserver, a library that
                provides a client and server implementation of VNC. </para>
            <example>
                <title>Building libguac-client-vnc from source</title>
                <screen><prompt>$</prompt> tar -xzf libguac-client-vnc-0.6.0.tar.gz
<prompt>$</prompt> cd libguac-client-vnc-0.6.0/
<prompt>$</prompt> ./configure
<prompt>$</prompt> make
<prompt>$</prompt> sudo make install
<prompt>$</prompt> sudo ldconfig              </screen>
            </example>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="compiling-libguac-client-rdp">
            <title>RDP support</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>compiling</primary>
                <secondary>RDP support</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>RDP support</primary>
                <secondary>compiling</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <para> RDP support in Guacamole requires FreeRDP, specifically
                FreeRDP version 1.0 or newer. The API of FreeRDP changed
                significantly after 1.0 (it was completely rewritten), thus
                Guacamole's RDP support (libguac-client-rdp) cannot be built
                against any older version. </para>
            <example>
                <title>Building libguac-client-rdp from source</title>
                <screen><prompt>$</prompt> tar -xzf libguac-client-rdp-0.6.1.tar.gz
<prompt>$</prompt> cd libguac-client-rdp-0.6.1/
<prompt>$</prompt> ./configure
<prompt>$</prompt> make
<prompt>$</prompt> sudo make install
<prompt>$</prompt> sudo ldconfig             </screen>
            </example>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="compiling-guacamole-war">
            <title>Building the web application (guacamole.war)</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>compiling</primary>
                <secondary>guacamole.war</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>guacamole.war</primary>
                <secondary>compiling</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>To compile the Java and Maven components of Guacamole
                (guacamole, guacamole-common, guacamole-ext, and
                guacamole-common-js), all you need is Apache Maven and a copy of
                the Java JDK, both of which most Linux distributions provide
                packages of. Because Java is cross-platform, this is generally
                not necessary unless you want to modify the Guacamole source.
                Even if you wish to modify the Guacamole web application, you
                still generally do not need to compile the other Java and Maven
                components, as Maven will automatically download compiled
                versions of those components from the official Maven repository
                of the Guacamole project:
                <uri>http://guac-dev.org/repo/</uri>.</para>
            <example>
                <title>Building Guacamole from source</title>
                <screen><prompt>$</prompt> tar -xzf guacamole-0.6.1.tar.gz
<prompt>$</prompt> cd guacamole-0.6.1/
<prompt>$</prompt> mvn package           </screen>
            </example>
            <para>Once the Guacamole web application is built, there will be a
                .war file in the <filename>target/</filename> subdirectory of
                the current directory (the directory you were in when you ran
                    <application>mvn</application>). This .war file contains the
                entirety of the Guacamole web application, including all
                dependencies. Installing Guacamole means copying this .war file
                into the directory required by your servlet container.</para>
            <example>
                <title>Installing Guacamole after building from source</title>
                <screen><prompt>$</prompt> sudo cp target/guacamole-0.6.0.war /var/lib/tomcat6/webapps/guacamole.war             </screen>
            </example>
            <para>The Guacamole web application also depends on a configuration
                file, <filename>guacamole.properties</filename>, to tell it the
                type of authentication to use and how to connect to guacd. A
                functional example <filename>guacamole.properties</filename> is
                contained in the <filename>doc/</filename> subdirectory; you can
                simply copy this somewhere (like
                    <filename>/etc/guacamole</filename>) and then create a
                symbolic link to it somewhere in your servlet container's
                classpath. Again, the precise location of the classpath will
                vary by distribution and servlet container.</para>
            <example>
                <title>Installing
                    <filename>guacamole.properties</filename></title>
                <screen><prompt>$</prompt> sudo mkdir /etc/guacamole
<prompt>$</prompt> sudo cp doc/guacamole.properties /etc/guacamole/guacamole.properties
<prompt>$</prompt> sudo ln -s /etc/guacamole/guacamole.properties /usr/share/tomcat6/lib/            </screen>
            </example>
            <para>You will need to edit
                    <filename>guacamole.properties</filename> to be sure that
                all the settings are valid for your installation.</para>
            <para>If you are using the default authentication method, you will
                also need to install the <filename>user-mapping.xml</filename>
                file. This file describes the users that should be allowed to
                log into Guacamole, as well as their passwords, and all
                corresponding remote desktop connections they should have access
                to.</para>
            <para>An example <filename>user-mapping.xml</filename> file is
                provided in the <filename>doc/</filename> subdirectory. You can
                simply copy this file to a reasonable location (like
                    <filename>/etc/guacamole/user-mapping.xml</filename>) and
                then edit <filename>guacamole.properties</filename> to specify
                the correct location of this file.</para>
            <para>You will need to edit <filename>user-mapping.xml</filename> to
                add and remove users, as well as to remove the "default" users
                included as examples.</para>
        </section>
    </section>

    <!--
    - From git 
    -->

    <section xml:id="git-repositories">
        <title>The absolute latest</title>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>git</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>unstable source</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>If you wish to build the absolute latest unstable code, you can do
            so by downloading the latest Guacamole code from git.</para>
        <para>The Guacamole project maintains each of its components in separate
            git repositories, which each have master (stable) and unstable
            (development) branches. To build and install the latest source, you
            need only clone the unstable branch of each repository, and then
            build as shown above.</para>
        <example>
            <title>Checking out Guacamole from git</title>
            <screen><prompt>$</prompt> git clone <uri>git://<replaceable>REPOSITORY</replaceable> -b unstable</uri>         </screen>
        </example>
        <para>As there are several repositories, you will run this git command
            to clone each of the repositories you wish to build. The URL of each
            repository is
                    <uri>git://guacamole.git.sourceforge.net/gitroot/guacamole/<replaceable>NAME</replaceable>/</uri>
            where <replaceable>NAME</replaceable> is any of the following
            repository names, each of which corresponds to the Guacamole
            component of the same name:<variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>libguac</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The core Guacamole library.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>libguac-client-vnc</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>VNC support plugin for guacd.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>libguac-client-rdp</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>RDP (Remote Desktop Protocol) support plugin for
                            guacd.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>guacd</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The proxy daemon which the web application,
                            Guacamole, communicates with.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>guacamole-common</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Common Java library used by Guacamole and
                            Guacamole-based web applications (when also written
                            in Java).</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>guacamole-common-js</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Common JavaScript library used by Guacamole and
                            Guacamole-based web applications.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>guacamole-ext</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Classes common to Guacamole and extensions/plugins
                            for Guacamole.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>guacamole</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Guacamole the web application; what most people
                            are referring to when they speak of software called
                            Guacamole.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist></para>
    </section>

</chapter>
