<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xml:id="libguac" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
    xml:lang="en" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <title>libguac</title>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>API</primary>
        <secondary>C</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>libguac</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>The C API for extending and developing with Guacamole is libguac. All
        native components produced by the Guacamole project link with this
        library, and this library provides the common basis for extending the
        native functionality of those native components (by implementing client
        plugins).</para>
    <para>libguac is used mainly for developing client plugins like
        libguac-client-vnc or libguac-client-rdp, or for developing a proxy
        supporting the Guacamole protocol like guacd. This chapter is intended
        to give an overview of how libguac is used, and how to use it for
        general communication with the Guacamole protocol.</para>
    <section xml:id="libguac-error-handling">
        <title>Error handling</title>
        <para>Most functions within libguac handle errors by returning a zero or
            non-zero value, whichever is appropriate for the function at hand.
            If an error is encountered, the <varname>guac_error</varname>
            variable is set appropriately, and
                <varname>guac_error_message</varname> contains a
            statically-allocated human-readable string describing the context of
            the error. These variables intentionally mimic the functionality
            provided by <varname>errno</varname> and
                <filename>errno.h</filename>.</para>
        <para>Both <varname>guac_error</varname> and
                <varname>guac_error_message</varname> are defined within
                <filename>error.h</filename>. A human-readable string describing
            the error indicated by <varname>guac_error</varname> can be
            retrieved using <methodname>guac_status_string()</methodname>, which
            is also statically allocated.</para>
        <para>If functions defined within client plugins set
                <varname>guac_error</varname> and
                <varname>guac_error_message</varname> appropriately when errors
            are encountered, the messages logged to syslog by guacd will be more
            meaningful for both users and developers.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="libguac-client-plugins">
        <title>Client plugins</title>
        <para>Client plugins are libraries loaded dynamically using the
            functions of libdl. Each client plugin is required to follow a
            naming convention, where the name of the library is
                    <package>libguac-client-<replaceable>PROTOCOL</replaceable></package>.
            Failing to do this means that guacd will be unable to find the
            library when the client plugin needs to be loaded.</para>
        <para>To load a client plugin, guacd calls the guac_client_plugin_open()
            function with the name of the protocol corresponding to the plugin
            to be loaded. Upon success,
                <methodname>guac_client_plugin_open()</methodname> returns a
            handle to the library containing the client plugin within an
            instance of <classname>guac_client_plugin</classname>. This instance
            will eventually be cleaned up by
                <methodname>guac_client_plugin_close()</methodname> when guacd
            is finished using it. While these functions are intended to be used
            by guacd, there is no reason they cannot be used in another proxy
            implementation, even if that proxy implementation resides within
            another client plugin.</para>
        <para>Once the client plugin is successfully loaded, guacd makes a call
            to <methodname>guac_client_plugin_init_client()</methodname> to
            initialize the client. This function calls the
                <methodname>guac_client_init()</methodname> function within the
            client plugin which absolutely all client plugins must define. This
            function is the entry point of all client plugins, similar to the
                <methodname>main()</methodname> function of a C program.</para>
        <para>As guacd handles the handshake procedure required by the Guacamole
            protocol, it reads a statically-allocated,
            <constant>NULL</constant>-terminated set of argument names declared
            within the client plugin: <varname>GUAC_CLIENT_ARGS</varname>. As
            with <methodname>guac_client_init()</methodname>, all client plugins
            must define this variable if they are to work. As the handshake
            procedure is completed, guacd will initialize and populate a
                <classname>guac_client</classname> structure, including the
                <classname>guac_client_info</classname> structure contained
            within it, and pass it to
                <methodname>guac_client_init()</methodname> along with the
            argument count and argument values received by the connecting
            client.</para>
        <para>It is the duty of the client plugin implementation to populate the
            event handlers of the <classname>guac_client</classname> it receives
            as applicable. Once this is done, and the
                <methodname>guac_client_init()</methodname> function returns
            successfully, communication with the connected client begins, and
            guacd will invoke the event handlers of the
                <classname>guac_client</classname> as necessary for any
            instruction received.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="libguac-layers">
        <title>Layers and buffers</title>
        <para>The main operand of all drawing instructions is the layer,
            represented within libguac by the <classname>guac_layer</classname>
            structure. Each <classname>guac_layer</classname> is normally
            allocated using <methodname>guac_client_alloc_layer()</methodname>
            or <methodname>guac_client_alloc_buffer()</methodname>, depending on
            whether a layer or buffer is desired, and freed with
                <methodname>guac_client_free_layer()</methodname> or
                <methodname>guac_client_free_buffer()</methodname>.</para>
        <important>
            <para>Care must be taken to invoke the allocate and free pairs of
                each type of layer correctly.
                    <methodname>guac_client_free_layer()</methodname> should
                only be used to free layers allocated with
                    <methodname>guac_client_alloc_layer()</methodname>, and
                    <methodname>guac_client_free_buffer()</methodname> should
                only be used to free layers allocated with
                    <methodname>guac_client_alloc_buffer()</methodname>, all
                called using the same instance of
                    <classname>guac_client</classname>.</para>
            <para>If these restrictions are not observed, the effect of invoking
                these functions is undefined.</para>
        </important>
        <para>Using these layer management functions allows you to reuse
            existing layers or buffers after their original purpose has expired,
            thus conserving resources on the client side, as allocation of new
            layers within the remote client is a relatively expensive
            operation.</para>
        <para>It is through layers and buffers that Guacamole provides support
            for hardware-accelerated compositing and cached updates. Creative
            use of layers and buffers leads to efficient updates on the client
            side, which usually translates into speed and responsiveness.</para>
        <para>Regardless of whether you allocate new layers or buffers, there is
            always one layer guaranteed to be present: the default layer,
            represented by libguac as <varname>GUAC_DEFAULT_LAYER</varname>. If
            you only wish to affect to the main display of the connected client
            somehow, this is the layer you want to use as the operand of your
            drawing instruction.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="libguac-sending-instructions">
        <title>Sending instructions</title>
        <para>All drawing in Guacamole is accomplished through the sending of
            instructions to the connected client using the Guacamole protocol.
            The same goes for streaming audio, video, or file content. All
            features and content supported by Guacamole ultimately reduces to
            one or more instructions which are part of the documented
            protocol.</para>
        <para>Most drawing using libguac is done using Cairo functions on a
                <classname>cairo_surface_t</classname> (see the Cairo API documentation) which is
            later streamed to the client using an <methodname>img</methodname> instruction and
            subsequent <methodname>blob</methodname> instructions, sent via
                <methodname>guac_client_stream_png()</methodname>. Cairo was chosen as a dependency
            of libguac to provide developers an existing and stable means of drawing to image
            buffers which will ultimately be sent as easy-to-digest PNG images.</para>
        <para>The Guacamole protocol also supports drawing primitives similar to
            those present in the Cairo API and HTML5's canvas tag. These
            instructions are documented individually in the Guacamole Protocol
            Reference in a section dedicated to drawing instructions, and like
            all Guacamole protocol instructions, each instruction has a
            corresponding function in libguac following the naming convention
                    <methodname>guac_protocol_send_<replaceable>OPCODE</replaceable>()</methodname>.</para>
        <para>Each protocol function takes a <classname>guac_socket</classname>
            as an argument, which is the buffered I/O object used by libguac.
            The <classname>guac_socket</classname> corresponding to the
            connected client is stored within the socket member of the
                <classname>guac_client</classname> object in use, for
            example:</para>
        <informalexample>
            <programlisting>guac_protocol_send_size(client->socket, GUAC_DEFAULT_LAYER, 1024, 768);</programlisting>
        </informalexample>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="libguac-protocol-nesting">
        <title>Protocol nesting</title>
        <para>When large instructions need to be sent, particularly those
            associated with audio or video, it is best to send those
            instructions broken into individual packets using nest instructions,
            such that the larger instruction can be interleaved with the smaller
            instructions such that normal responsiveness is not lessened. As
            future instructions cannot be parsed until the earlier instructions
            finish parsing, avoiding large instructions is important if the user
            is expected to interact with their display in real-time.</para>
        <para>libguac provides rudimentary means of automatically nesting
            instructions using the <methodname>guac_socket_nest()</methodname>
            function. This function returns a new
                <classname>guac_socket</classname> which writes data to nest
            instructions to its parent <classname>guac_socket</classname>,
            rather than to the client's stream directly. By using this and the
            piecemeal versions of the instruction-sending functions required,
            audio or video data can be stretched over multiple instructions
            rather than one single instruction:</para>
        <informalexample>
            <programlisting>/* Get nested socket */
guac_socket* nested_socket = guac_socket_nest(client->socket, 0);

/* Write audio header */
guac_protocol_send_audio_header(nested_socket,
    0, "audio/ogg", 250, buffer_size);

...

/* Write data packets */
guac_protocol_send_audio_data(nested_socket, data, sizeof(data));

...

/* Finish audio instruction */
guac_protocol_send_audio_end(nested_socket);

/* When done, close the socket */
guac_socket_close(nested_socket);</programlisting>
        </informalexample>
        <para>Providing that calls to guac_protocol_send_audio_data() (or the
            similar video functions) are made interleaved with calls to smaller
            instructions, those smaller instructions will not be blocked by the
            size of the audio data that must be sent.</para>
        <important>
            <para>Because of the nature of the Guacamole protocol, the size and
                duration of audio or video data must be known beforehand. If
                audio or video data must be streamed in real-time, it will need
                to be divided into individual self-contained chunks. Smaller
                chunks have a greater chance of causing noticeable gaps due to
                network hiccups, but are more responsive and will seem more
                in-line with what is happening from the user's perspective,
                while larger chunks will be less vulnerable to network issues,
                but obviously will require the client to wait for a longer time
                before the audio or video actually starts playing.</para>
            <para>Note that the size of each audio or video packet is not
                related to the size of each nest instruction. Choosing larger
                audio or video packets does not mean that the nest instruction
                cannot be used; in fact, this is the purpose of the nest
                instruction: to allow larger instructions to be broken up into
                smaller instructions.</para>
        </important>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="libguac-event-handling">
        <title>Event handling</title>
        <para>Generally, as guacd receives instructions from the connected
            client, it invokes event handlers if set within the associated
                <classname>guac_client</classname> instance. These handlers
            correspond to the instructions received, which in turn correspond to
            events which occur on the client side. The only exception to this is
            when guacd wishes to give the client plugin control and allow it to
            handle any messages that may have arrived from the remote desktop
            server, in which case it invokes a specific event handler dedicated
            to this purpose.</para>
        <section xml:id="libguac-key-events">
            <title>Key events</title>
            <para>When keys are pressed or released on the client side, the
                client sends key instructions to the server. These instructions
                are parsed and handled by calling the key event handler
                installed in the <property>key_handler</property> member of the
                    <classname>guac_client</classname>. This key handler is
                given the keysym of the key that was changed, and a boolean
                value indicating whether the key was pressed or released.</para>
            <informalexample>
                <programlisting>int key_handler(guac_client* client, int keysym, int pressed) {
    /* Do something */
}

...

/* Within guac_client_init */
client->key_handler = key_handler;</programlisting>
            </informalexample>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="libguac-mouse-events">
            <title>Mouse events</title>
            <para>When the mouse is moved, and buttons are pressed or released,
                the client sends mouse instructions to the server. These
                instructions are parsed and handled by calling the mouse event
                handler installed in the <property>mouse_handler</property>
                member of the <classname>guac_client</classname>. This mouse
                handler is given the current X and Y coordinates of the mouse
                pointer, as well as a mask indicating which buttons are pressed
                and which are released.</para>
            <informalexample>
                <programlisting>int mouse_handler(guac_client* client, int x, int y, int button_mask) {
    /* Do something */
}

...

/* Within guac_client_init */
client->mouse_handler = mouse_handler;</programlisting>
            </informalexample>
            <para>The file <filename>client.h</filename> also defines the mask
                of each button for convenience:</para>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><constant>GUAC_CLIENT_MOUSE_LEFT</constant></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The left mouse button, set when pressed.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><constant>GUAC_CLIENT_MOUSE_MIDDLE</constant></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The middle mouse button, set when pressed.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><constant>GUAC_CLIENT_MOUSE_RIGHT</constant></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The right mouse button, set when pressed.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><constant>GUAC_CLIENT_MOUSE_UP</constant></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The button corresponding to one scroll in the
                            upwards direction of the mouse scroll wheel, set
                            when scrolled.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><constant>GUAC_CLIENT_MOUSE_DOWN</constant></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The button corresponding to one scroll in the
                            downwards direction of the mouse scroll wheel, set
                            when scrolled.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="libguac-clipboard-events">
            <title>Clipboard events</title>
            <para>If the client sends data which should be sent to the clipboard
                of the remote desktop, guacd will trigger the clipboard handler
                installed in the <property>clipboard_handler</property> member
                of the <classname>guac_client</classname>.</para>
            <informalexample>
                <programlisting>int clipboard_handler(guac_client* client, char* text) {
    /* Do something */
}

...

/* Within guac_client_init */
client->clipboard_handler = clipboard_handler;</programlisting>
            </informalexample>
            <para>The data given will always be a
                <constant>NULL</constant>-terminated string of UTF8-encoded
                text. The Guacamole protocol does not yet support clipboard data
                in other formats.</para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="libguac-message-handling">
            <title>Handling server messages</title>
            <para>A client plugin implementation is expected to only handle
                server messages when control is given to it via a call to the
                message handler installed in the
                    <property>handle_messages</property> member of the
                    <classname>guac_client</classname>. While it might seem
                intuitive to simply create a thread which handles server message
                in the background, it is important that you do not do this, as
                guacd pays attention to the exchange of sync instructions back
                and forth between itself and the client to determine if the
                client is under load or falling behind due to network problems,
                and will restrict how frequently the message handler is called
                accordingly. Ignoring this can lead to the client being
                overwhelmed with instructions, leading to a bad user
                experience.</para>
            <para>The message handler is simpler than all the other handlers,
                receiving only a pointer to the current
                    <classname>guac_client</classname>:</para>
            <informalexample>
                <programlisting>int message_handler(guac_client* client) {
    /* Handle server messages */
}

...

/* Within guac_client_init */
client->handle_messages = message_handler;</programlisting>
            </informalexample>
        </section>
    </section>
</chapter>
