<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xml:id="libguac" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
    xml:lang="en" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <title>libguac</title>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>API</primary>
        <secondary>C</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>libguac</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>The C API for extending and developing with Guacamole is libguac. All
        native components produced by the Guacamole project link with this
        library, and this library provides the common basis for extending the
        native functionality of those native components (by implementing client
        plugins).</para>
    <para>libguac is used mainly for developing client plugins like
        libguac-client-vnc or libguac-client-rdp, or for developing a proxy
        supporting the Guacamole protocol like guacd. This chapter is intended
        to give an overview of how libguac is used, and how to use it for
        general communication with the Guacamole protocol.</para>
    <section xml:id="libguac-error-handling">
        <title>Error handling</title>
        <para>Most functions within libguac handle errors by returning a zero or
            non-zero value, whichever is appropriate for the function at hand.
            If an error is encountered, the <varname>guac_error</varname>
            variable is set appropriately, and
                <varname>guac_error_message</varname> contains a
            statically-allocated human-readable string describing the context of
            the error. These variables intentionally mimic the functionality
            provided by <varname>errno</varname> and
                <filename>errno.h</filename>.</para>
        <para>Both <varname>guac_error</varname> and
                <varname>guac_error_message</varname> are defined within
                <filename>error.h</filename>. A human-readable string describing
            the error indicated by <varname>guac_error</varname> can be
            retrieved using <methodname>guac_status_string()</methodname>, which
            is also statically allocated.</para>
        <para>If functions defined within client plugins set
                <varname>guac_error</varname> and
                <varname>guac_error_message</varname> appropriately when errors
            are encountered, the messages logged to syslog by guacd will be more
            meaningful for both users and developers.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="libguac-client-plugins">
        <title>Client plugins</title>
        <para>Client plugins are libraries which follow specific conventions such that they can be
            loaded dynamically by guacd. All client plugins <emphasis>must</emphasis>:</para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Follow a naming convention, where the name of the library is
                            <package>libguac-client-<replaceable>PROTOCOL</replaceable></package>.
                        <emphasis>This is necessary for guacd to locate the library for a requested
                        protocol.</emphasis></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Be linked against libguac, the library used by guacd to handle the Guacamole
                    protocol. The structures which are given to functions invoked by guacd are
                    defined by libguac, and are expected to be manipulated via the functions
                    provided by libguac or as otherwise documented within the structure itself.
                        <emphasis>Communication between guacd and client plugins is only possible if
                        they share the same core structural and functional definitions provided by
                        libguac.</emphasis></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Implement the standard entry point for client plugins,
                        <methodname>guac_client_init()</methodname>, described in more detail below.
                    It is this function which initializes the structures provided by guacd such that
                    users can join and interact with the connection.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <section xml:id="libguac-lifecycle-entry">
            <title>Entry point</title>
            <para>All client plugins must provide a function named
                    <methodname>guac_client_init</methodname> which accepts, as its sole argument, a
                pointer to a <classname>guac_client</classname> structure. This function is similar
                in principle to the <methodname>main()</methodname> function of a C program, and it
                is the responsibility of this function to initialize the provided structure as
                necessary to begin the actual remote desktop connection, allow users to join/leave,
                etc.</para>
            <para>The provided <classname>guac_client</classname> will already have been initialized
                with handlers for logging, the broadcast socket, etc. The absolutely critical pieces
                which must be provided by <methodname>guac_client_init</methodname> are:</para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>A handler for users which join the connection
                            (<property>join_handler</property>). The join handler is also usually
                        the most appropriate place for the actual remote desktop connection to be
                        established.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>A <constant>NULL</constant>-terminated set of argument names which the
                        client plugin accepts, assigned to the <property>args</property> property of
                        the given <classname>guac_client</classname>. As the handshake procedure is
                        completed for each connecting user, these argument names will be presented
                        as part of the handshake, and the values for those arguments will be passed
                        to the join handler once the handshake completes.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>A handler for users leaving the connection
                            (<property>leave_handler</property>), if any cleanup, updates, etc. are
                        required.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>A handler for freeing the data associated with the
                            <classname>guac_client</classname> after the connection has terminated
                            (<property>free_handler</property>). If your plugin will allocate any
                        data at all, implementing the free handler is necessary to avoid memory
                        leaks.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <para>If <methodname>guac_client_init</methodname> returns successfully, guacd will
                proceed with allowing the first use to join the connection, and the rest of the
                plugin lifecycle commences.</para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="libguac-lifecycle-users">
            <title>Joining/leaving a connection</title>
            <para>Whenever a user joins a connection, including the very first user of a connection
                (the user which is establishing the remote desktop connection in the first place),
                the join handler of the <property>guac_client</property> will be invoked. This
                handler is provided with the <classname>guac_user</classname> structure representing
                the user that just joined, along with the arguments provided during the handshake
                procedure:</para>
            <informalexample>
                <programlisting>int join_handler(guac_user* user, int argc, char** argv) {
    /* Synchronize display state, init the user, etc. */
}

...

/* Within guac_client_init  */
client->join_handler = join_handler;</programlisting>
            </informalexample>
            <para>As the parameters and user information provided during the Guacamole protocol
                handshake are often required to be known before the remote desktop connection can be
                established, the join handler is usually the best place to create a thread which
                establishes the remote desktop connection and updates the display
                accordingly.</para>
            <para>If necessary, the user which first established the connection can be distinguished
                from all other users by the <property>owner</property> flag of
                    <classname>guac_user</classname>, which will be set to a non-zero value.</para>
            <para>Once a user has disconnected, the leave handler of
                    <classname>guac_client</classname> will be invoked. Just as with the join
                handler, this handler is provided the <classname>guac_user</classname> structure of
                the user that disconnected. The <classname>guac_user</classname> structure will be
                freed immediately after the handler completes:</para>
            <informalexample>
                <programlisting>int leave_handler(guac_user* user) {
    /* Free user-specific data and clean up */
}

...

/* Within guac_client_init  */
client->leave_handler = leave_handler;</programlisting>
            </informalexample>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="libguac-lifecycle-termination">
            <title>Termination</title>
            <para>Once the last user of a connection has left, guacd will begin freeing resources
                allocated to that connection, invoking the free handler of the
                    <classname>guac_client</classname>. At this point, the "leave" handler has been
                invoked for all previous users. All that remains is for the client plugin to free
                any remaining data that it allocated, such that guacd can clean up the rest:</para>
            <informalexample>
                <programlisting>int free_handler(guac_client* client) {
    /* Disconnect, free client-specific data, etc. */
}

...

/* Within guac_client_init  */
client->free_handler = free_handler;</programlisting>
            </informalexample>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="libguac-layers">
        <title>Layers and buffers</title>
        <para>The main operand of all drawing instructions is the layer,
            represented within libguac by the <classname>guac_layer</classname>
            structure. Each <classname>guac_layer</classname> is normally
            allocated using <methodname>guac_client_alloc_layer()</methodname>
            or <methodname>guac_client_alloc_buffer()</methodname>, depending on
            whether a layer or buffer is desired, and freed with
                <methodname>guac_client_free_layer()</methodname> or
                <methodname>guac_client_free_buffer()</methodname>.</para>
        <important>
            <para>Care must be taken to invoke the allocate and free pairs of
                each type of layer correctly.
                    <methodname>guac_client_free_layer()</methodname> should
                only be used to free layers allocated with
                    <methodname>guac_client_alloc_layer()</methodname>, and
                    <methodname>guac_client_free_buffer()</methodname> should
                only be used to free layers allocated with
                    <methodname>guac_client_alloc_buffer()</methodname>, all
                called using the same instance of
                    <classname>guac_client</classname>.</para>
            <para>If these restrictions are not observed, the effect of invoking
                these functions is undefined.</para>
        </important>
        <para>Using these layer management functions allows you to reuse
            existing layers or buffers after their original purpose has expired,
            thus conserving resources on the client side, as allocation of new
            layers within the remote client is a relatively expensive
            operation.</para>
        <para>It is through layers and buffers that Guacamole provides support
            for hardware-accelerated compositing and cached updates. Creative
            use of layers and buffers leads to efficient updates on the client
            side, which usually translates into speed and responsiveness.</para>
        <para>Regardless of whether you allocate new layers or buffers, there is
            always one layer guaranteed to be present: the default layer,
            represented by libguac as <varname>GUAC_DEFAULT_LAYER</varname>. If
            you only wish to affect to the main display of the connected client
            somehow, this is the layer you want to use as the operand of your
            drawing instruction.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="libguac-sending-instructions">
        <title>Sending instructions</title>
        <para>All drawing in Guacamole is accomplished through the sending of instructions to the
            connected client using the Guacamole protocol. The same goes for streaming audio, video,
            or file content. All features and content supported by Guacamole ultimately reduce to
            one or more instructions which are part of the documented protocol.</para>
        <para>Most drawing using libguac is done using Cairo functions on a
                <classname>cairo_surface_t</classname> (see the Cairo API documentation) which is
            later streamed to the client using an <methodname>img</methodname> instruction and
            subsequent <methodname>blob</methodname> instructions, sent via
                <methodname>guac_client_stream_png()</methodname>. Cairo was chosen as a dependency
            of libguac to provide developers an existing and stable means of drawing to image
            buffers which will ultimately be sent as easy-to-digest PNG images.</para>
        <para>The Guacamole protocol also supports drawing primitives similar to
            those present in the Cairo API and HTML5's canvas tag. These
            instructions are documented individually in the Guacamole Protocol
            Reference in a section dedicated to drawing instructions, and like
            all Guacamole protocol instructions, each instruction has a
            corresponding function in libguac following the naming convention
                    <methodname>guac_protocol_send_<replaceable>OPCODE</replaceable>()</methodname>.</para>
        <para>Each protocol function takes a <classname>guac_socket</classname> as an argument,
            which is the buffered I/O object used by libguac. For each active connection, there are
            two important types of <classname>guac_socket</classname> instance: the broadcast
            socket, which exists at the client level within the <classname>guac_client</classname>,
            and the per-user socket, which is accessible within each
                <classname>guac_user</classname>. Data sent along the client-level broadcast socket
            will be sent to all connected users beneath that <classname>guac_client</classname>,
            while data sent along a user-level socket will be sent only to that user.</para>
        <para>For example, to send a "size" instruction to all connected users via the client-level
            broadcast socket, you could invoke:</para>
        <informalexample>
            <programlisting>guac_protocol_send_size(client->socket, GUAC_DEFAULT_LAYER, 1024, 768);</programlisting>
        </informalexample>
        <para>Or, if the instruction is only relevant to a particular user, the socket associated
            with that user can be used instead:</para>
        <informalexample>
            <programlisting>guac_protocol_send_size(<emphasis>user</emphasis>->socket, GUAC_DEFAULT_LAYER, 1024, 768);</programlisting>
        </informalexample>
        <para>The sockets provided by libguac are threadsafe at the protocol level. Instructions
            written to a socket by multiple threads are guaranteed to be written atomically with
            respect to that socket.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="libguac-event-handling">
        <title>Event handling</title>
        <para>Generally, as guacd receives instructions from the connected client, it invokes event
            handlers if set within the associated <classname>guac_user</classname> or
                <classname>guac_client</classname>, depending on the nature of the event. Most
            events are user-specific, and thus the event handlers reside within the
                <classname>guac_user</classname> structure, but there are client-specific events as
            well, such as a user joining or leaving the current connection. Event handlers typically
            correspond to Guacamole protocol instructions received over the socket by a connected
            user, which in turn correspond to events which occur on the client side.</para>
        <section xml:id="libguac-key-events">
            <title>Key events</title>
            <para>When keys are pressed or released on the client side, the client sends key
                instructions to the server. These instructions are parsed and handled by calling the
                key event handler installed in the <property>key_handler</property> member of the
                    <classname>guac_user</classname>. This key handler is given the keysym of the
                key that was changed, and a boolean value indicating whether the key was pressed or
                released.</para>
            <informalexample>
                <programlisting>int key_handler(guac_user* user, int keysym, int pressed) {
    /* Do something */
}

...

/* Within the "join" handler of guac_client */
user->key_handler = key_handler;</programlisting>
            </informalexample>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="libguac-mouse-events">
            <title>Mouse events</title>
            <para>When the mouse is moved, and buttons are pressed or released, the client sends
                mouse instructions to the server. These instructions are parsed and handled by
                calling the mouse event handler installed in the <property>mouse_handler</property>
                member of the <classname>guac_user</classname>. This mouse handler is given the
                current X and Y coordinates of the mouse pointer, as well as a mask indicating which
                buttons are pressed and which are released.</para>
            <informalexample>
                <programlisting>int mouse_handler(guac_user* user, int x, int y, int button_mask) {
    /* Do something */
}

...

/* Within the "join" handler of guac_client */
user->mouse_handler = mouse_handler;</programlisting>
            </informalexample>
            <para>The file <filename>client.h</filename> also defines the mask
                of each button for convenience:</para>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><constant>GUAC_CLIENT_MOUSE_LEFT</constant></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The left mouse button, set when pressed.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><constant>GUAC_CLIENT_MOUSE_MIDDLE</constant></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The middle mouse button, set when pressed.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><constant>GUAC_CLIENT_MOUSE_RIGHT</constant></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The right mouse button, set when pressed.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><constant>GUAC_CLIENT_MOUSE_UP</constant></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The button corresponding to one scroll in the
                            upwards direction of the mouse scroll wheel, set
                            when scrolled.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><constant>GUAC_CLIENT_MOUSE_DOWN</constant></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The button corresponding to one scroll in the
                            downwards direction of the mouse scroll wheel, set
                            when scrolled.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="libguac-clipboard-events">
            <title>Clipboard events</title>
            <para>If a connected user sends data which should be sent to the clipboard of the remote
                desktop, guacd will trigger the clipboard handler installed in the
                    <property>clipboard_handler</property> member of the
                    <classname>guac_user</classname> associated with that user.</para>
            <informalexample>
                <programlisting>int clipboard_handler(guac_user* user, guac_stream* stream, char* mimetype) {
    /* Do something */
}

...

/* Within the "join" handler of guac_client */
user->clipboard_handler = clipboard_handler;</programlisting>
            </informalexample>
        </section>
    </section>
</chapter>
