<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<chapter xml:id="noauth" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="en"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <title>Disabling authentication</title>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>disabling authentication</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>NoAuth</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>Guacamole normally enforces authentication, requiring all users to have a corresponding
        set of credentials. If you would rather just type in your server's URL and gain access to
        your computer, you can do this with the so-called "NoAuth" extension.</para>
    <para>The NoAuth extension still performs authentication, but does not validate any credentials,
        giving anyone that visits your server access to the same set of connections dictated by an
        XML configuration file. It is an authentication implementation in its own right, and thus
        doesn't truly "disable" authentication. It simply grants anyone access without requesting a
        username or password.</para>
    <important>
        <para>The security implications of this should be obvious - anyone with access to your
            Guacamole instance will have access to your remote desktops. If you wish to effectively
            disable authentication using NoAuth, do so with caution.</para>
    </important>
    <section>
        <title>Downloading the NoAuth extension</title>
        <para xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">The NoAuth authentication extension is
            available separately from the main <filename>guacamole.war</filename>. The link for this
            and all other officially-supported and compatible extensions for a particular version of
            Guacamole are provided on the release notes for that version. You can find the release
            notes for current versions of Guacamole here: <link
                xlink:href="http://guac-dev.org/releases/"
            >http://guac-dev.org/releases/</link>.</para>
        <para xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">The NoAuth authentication extension is
            packaged as a <filename>.tar.gz</filename> file containing:</para>
        <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><filename>guacamole-auth-noauth-0.9.6.jar</filename></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The NoAuth extension itself, which must be placed in
                            <filename>GUACAMOLE_HOME/extensions</filename>.</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><filename>doc/example/</filename></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Contains an example configuration file:
                            <filename>noauth-config.xml</filename>.</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="installing-noauth">
        <title>Installing the NoAuth extension</title>
        <para>Guacamole extensions are self-contained <filename>.jar</filename> files which are
            located within the <filename>GUACAMOLE_HOME/extensions</filename> directory. To install
            the NoAuth authentication extension, you must:</para>
        <procedure>
            <step>
                <para>Create the <filename>GUACAMOLE_HOME/extensions</filename> directory, if it
                    does not already exist.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Remove any existing authentication extensions from
                        <filename>GUACAMOLE_HOME/extensions</filename>. Guacamole does not currently
                    support using multiple authentication extensions at the same time.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Copy <filename>guacamole-auth-noauth-0.9.6.jar</filename> within
                        <filename>GUACAMOLE_HOME/extensions</filename>.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Configure Guacamole to use NoAuth, as described below.</para>
            </step>
        </procedure>
        <important>
            <para>You will need to restart Guacamole by restarting your servlet container in order
                to complete the installation. Doing this will disconnect all active users, so be
                sure that it is safe to do so prior to attempting installation. If you do not
                configure the NoAuth extension properly, Guacamole will not start up again until the
                configuration is fixed.</para>
        </important>
        <section>
            <title>Configuring Guacamole for NoAuth</title>
            <para>An additional property must be added to <filename>guacamole.properties</filename>
                such that Guacamole will load the NoAuth extension and locate its configuration
                file:</para>
            <programlisting># NoAuth properties
noauth-config: <replaceable>/etc/guacamole/noauth-config.xml</replaceable></programlisting>
            <para>The <property>noauth-config</property> property defines the location of the XML
                configuration file required by NoAuth. This file describes the connections available
                to any user of your Guacamole instance and can be placed anywhere so long as its
                location is given in <filename>guacamole.properties</filename>. On Linux servers,
                    <filename>/etc/guacamole</filename> is a good location for Guacamole
                configuration files, including the configuration file used by NoAuth.</para>
            <section xml:id="noauth-configuration">
                <title>The NoAuth configuration file</title>
                <indexterm>
                    <primary>configuring NoAuth</primary>
                </indexterm>
                <para>Although the NoAuth extension does not check credentials, it still requires a
                    configuration file describing which connections are available and the protocols
                    to use. This configuration is an XML file, typically called
                        <filename>noauth-config.xml</filename>.</para>
                <para>An example configuration file is provided in the
                        <filename>doc/example/</filename> directory of the
                        <filename>.tar.gz</filename> file downloadable from the Guacamole site. The
                    format is fairly straightforward, and consists only of a list of connections
                    (configurations) and parameters:</para>
                <informalexample>
                    <programlisting>&lt;configs>
    &lt;config name="myconfig" protocol="rdp">
        &lt;param name="hostname" value="rdp-server" />
        &lt;param name="port" value="3389" />
    &lt;/config>
&lt;/configs></programlisting>
                    <para>The file consists of a single <code>&lt;configs></code> tag that contains
                        any number of <code>&lt;config></code> tags, each representing a distinct
                        connection available for use.</para>
                    <para>Each <code>&lt;config></code> tag has a corresponding <code>name</code>
                        and <code>protocol</code>. The <code>name</code> attribute defines a unique
                        identifier for the connection and tells Guacamole what text should be
                        displayed when identifying the connection. The <code>protocol</code>
                        attribute defines the standard remote desktop protocol to use, such as
                            "<constant>vnc</constant>", "<constant>rdp</constant>", or
                            "<constant>ssh</constant>". These protocols must be specified as
                        lowercase due to the naming convention used by the libraries providing
                        protocol support. If the wrong case is used, Guacamole will be unable to
                        load the corresponding protocol support and the connection will fail.</para>
                    <para>The <code>&lt;param></code> tags are placed within
                            <code>&lt;config></code> tags, describing a parameter name/value pair.
                        The parameters available, their names, and their allowed values are
                        protocol-specific and documented in <xref linkend="configuring-guacamole"
                        />.</para>
                    <para>The example above creates a new connection called "myconfig" that uses RDP
                        to connect to the server at "rdp-server" on port 3389.</para>
                </informalexample>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Completing the installation</title>
            <para>Guacamole will only reread <filename>guacamole.properties</filename> and load
                newly-installed extensions during startup, so your servlet container will need to be
                restarted before the disabled authentication will take effect. Restart your servlet
                container and check whether your changes have been successful.</para>
            <para>
                <important>
                    <para>You only need to restart your servlet container. <emphasis>You do not need
                            to restart <package>guacd</package></emphasis>.</para>
                    <para><package>guacd</package> is completely independent of the web application
                        and does not deal with <filename>guacamole.properties</filename> or the
                        authentication system in any way. Since you are already restarting the
                        servlet container, restarting <package>guacd</package> as well technically
                        won't hurt anything, but doing so is completely pointless.</para>
                </important>
            </para>
            <para>If Guacamole does not come back online after restarting your servlet container, or
                you are prompted for a username and password, check the logs. Problems in the
                configuration of NoAuth extension will prevent Guacamole from starting up, and any
                such errors will be recorded in the logs of your servlet container.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
</chapter>
