<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<chapter xml:id="rdp-support" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    version="5.0" xml:lang="en" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <title>RDP</title>
    <para>The RDP protocol is more complicated than VNC and was the second
        protocol officially supported by Guacamole. RDP tends to be faster than
        VNC due to the use of caching, which Guacamole does take advantage
        of.</para>
    <para>RDP support for Guacamole is provided by the
            <package>libguac-client-rdp</package> library, which depends on a
        recent version of FreeRDP (version 1.0 or higher). If your distribution
        does not have a recent enough version of FreeRDP, the Guacamole project
        will not build a <package>libguac-client-rdp</package> package for you.
        You will need to build and install a recent version of FreeRDP, and then
        build and install <package>libguac-client-rdp</package> from
        source.</para>
    <section xml:id="rdp-parameters">
        <title>Configuration parameters</title>
        <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><parameter>hostname</parameter></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The hostname or IP address of the RDP server Guacamole
                        should connect to.</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><parameter>port</parameter></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The port the RDP server is listening on, usually 3389.
                        This parameter is optional. If this is not specified,
                        the default of 3389 will be used.</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><parameter>username</parameter></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The username to use to authenticate, if any. This
                        parameter is optional.</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><parameter>password</parameter></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The password to use when attempting authentication, if
                        any. This parameter is optional.</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><parameter>domain</parameter></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The domain to use when attempting authentication, if
                        any. This parameter is optional.</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><parameter>color-depth</parameter></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The color depth to request, in bits-per-pixel. This
                        parameter is optional. If specified, this must be either
                        8, 16, or 24. Regardless of what value is chosen here,
                        if a particular update uses less than 256 colors,
                        Guacamole will always send that update as a 256-color
                        PNG.</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><parameter>width</parameter></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The width of the display to request, in pixels. This
                        parameter is optional. If this value is not specified,
                        the width of the connecting client display will be used
                        instead.</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><parameter>height</parameter></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The height of the display to request, in pixels. This
                        parameter is optional. If this value is not specified,
                        the height of the connecting client display will be used
                        instead.</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><parameter>disable-audio</parameter></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>As of Guacamole version 0.7.0, audio is officially
                        support and enabled by default in both the client and in
                        libguac-client-rdp. If you are concerned about bandwidth
                        usage, or sound is causing problems, you can explicitly
                        disable sound by setting this parameter to
                        "true".</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><parameter>console</parameter></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>If set to "true", you will be connected to the console
                        (admin) session of the RDP server.</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><parameter>console-audio</parameter></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>If set to "true", audio will be explicitly enabled in
                        the console (admin) session of the RDP server. Setting
                        this option to "true" only makes sense if the
                            <parameter>console</parameter> parameter is also set
                        to "true".</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="adding-rdp">
        <title>Adding an RDP connection</title>
        <para/>
    </section>
</chapter>
