<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xml:id="proxying-guacamole" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
    xml:lang="en" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <title>Proxying Guacamole</title>
    <para>Like most web applications, Guacamole can be placed behind a reverse proxy. For production
        deployments of Guacamole, this is <emphasis>highly recommended</emphasis>. It provides
        flexibility and, if your proxy is properly configured for SSL, encryption.</para>
    <para>Proxying isolates privileged operations within native applications that can safely drop
        those privileges when no longer needed, using Java only for unprivileged tasks. On Linux and
        UNIX systems, a process must be running with root privileges to listen on any port under
        1024, including the standard HTTP and HTTPS ports (80 and 443 respectively). If the servlet
        container instead listens on a higher port, such as the default port 8080, it can run as a
        reduced-privilege user, allowing the reverse proxy to bear the burden of root privileges. As
        a native application, the reverse proxy can make system calls to safely drop root privileges
        once the port is open; a Java application like Tomcat cannot do this.</para>
    <section>
        <title>Preparing your servlet container</title>
        <para>Your servlet container is most likely already configured to listen for HTTP
            connections on port 8080 as this is the default. If this is the case, and you can
            already access Guacamole over port 8080 from a web browser, you need not make any
            further changes to its configuration.</para>
        <para>If you <emphasis>have</emphasis> changed this, perhaps with the intent of proxying
            Guacamole over AJP, <emphasis>change it back</emphasis>. Using Guacamole over AJP is
            unsupported as it is known to cause problems, namely:</para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>WebSocket will not work over AJP, forcing Guacamole to fallback to HTTP,
                    possibly resulting in reduced performance.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Apache 2.4.3 and older does not support the HTTP PATCH method over AJP,
                    preventing the Guacamole management interface from functioning properly.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>The connector entry within <filename>conf/server.xml</filename> should look like
            this:</para>
        <informalexample>
            <programlisting>&lt;Connector port="8080" protocol="HTTP/1.1" 
           connectionTimeout="20000"
           URIEncoding="UTF-8"
           redirectPort="8443" /></programlisting>
        </informalexample>
        <para>Be sure to specify the <code>URIEncoding="UTF-8"</code> attribute as above to ensure
            that connection names, user names, etc. are properly received by the web application. If
            you will be creating connections that have Cyrillic, Chinese, Japanese, or other
            non-Latin characters in their names or parameter values, this attribute is
            required.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="nginx">
        <title>Nginx</title>
        <para>Nginx can be used as a reverse proxy, and supports WebSocket out-of-the-box <link
                xl:href="http://nginx.com/blog/websocket-nginx/">since version 1.3</link>. Both
            Apache and Nginx require some additional configuration for proxying of WebSocket to work
            properly.</para>
        <section>
            <title>Configuring WebSocket</title>
            <para/>
            <informalexample>
                <programlisting>map $http_upgrade $connection_upgrade {
    default upgrade;
    ''      close;
}</programlisting>
            </informalexample>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Proxying Guacamole</title>
            <para/>
            <informalexample>
                <programlisting>location /guacamole/ {
    proxy_pass http://<replaceable>HOSTNAME</replaceable>:<replaceable>8080</replaceable>/guacamole/;
    proxy_buffering off;
    proxy_http_version 1.1;
    proxy_set_header X-Forwarded-For $proxy_add_x_forwarded_for;
    proxy_set_header Upgrade $http_upgrade;
    proxy_set_header Connection $connection_upgrade;
    access_log off;
}</programlisting>
            </informalexample>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Changing the path</title>
            <para/>
            <informalexample>
                <programlisting>location /<replaceable>new-path/</replaceable> {
    proxy_pass http://<replaceable>HOSTNAME</replaceable>:<replaceable>8080</replaceable>/guacamole/;
    proxy_buffering off;
    proxy_http_version 1.1;
    proxy_set_header X-Forwarded-For $proxy_add_x_forwarded_for;
    proxy_set_header Upgrade $http_upgrade;
    proxy_set_header Connection $connection_upgrade;
    proxy_cookie_path /guacamole/ /<replaceable>new-path/</replaceable>;
    access_log off;
}</programlisting>
            </informalexample>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="mod-proxy">
        <title>Apache and <package>mod_proxy</package></title>
        <para>Apache supports reverse proxy configurations through <link
                xl:href="http://httpd.apache.org/docs/2.4/mod/mod_proxy.html"
                    ><package>mod_proxy</package></link>. Apache 2.4.5 and later also support
            proxying of WebSocket through a sub-module called <link
                xl:href="http://httpd.apache.org/docs/2.4/mod/mod_proxy_wstunnel.html"
                    ><package>mod_proxy_wstunnel</package></link>. Both of these modules will need
            to be enabled for proxying of Guacamole to work properly.</para>
        <para>Lacking <package>mod_proxy_wstunnel</package>, it is still possible to proxy
            Guacamole, but Guacamole will be unable to use WebSocket. It will instead fallback to
            using the HTTP tunnel, resulting in reduced performance.</para>
        <section>
            <title>Proxying Guacamole</title>
            <para>Configuring Apache to proxy HTTP requests requires using the
                    <parameter>ProxyPass</parameter> and <parameter>ProxyPassReverse</parameter>
                directives, which are provided by the <package>mod_proxy</package> module. These
                directives describe how HTTP traffic should be routed to the web server behind the
                proxy:</para>
            <informalexample>
                <programlisting>&lt;Location /guacamole/>
    Order allow,deny
    Allow from all
    ProxyPass http://<replaceable>HOSTNAME</replaceable>:<replaceable>8080</replaceable>/guacamole/ flushpackets=on
    ProxyPassReverse http://<replaceable>HOSTNAME</replaceable>:<replaceable>8080</replaceable>/guacamole/
&lt;/Location></programlisting>
            </informalexample>
            <important>
                <para><emphasis>Do not forget the <option>flushpackets=on</option>
                        option.</emphasis></para>
                <para>Most proxies, including <package>mod_proxy</package>, will buffer all data
                    sent over the connection, waiting until the connection is closed before sending
                    that data to the client. As Guacamole's HTTP tunnel relies on streaming data to
                    the client over an open connection, excessive buffering will effectively block
                    Guacamole connections, rendering Guacamole useless.</para>
                <para><emphasis>If the option <option>flushpackets=on</option> is not specified,
                        Guacamole will not work</emphasis>.</para>
            </important>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Proxying the WebSocket tunnel</title>
            <para>Apache will not automatically proxy WebSocket connections, but you can proxy them
                separately with Apache 2.4.5 and later using <package>mod_proxy_wstunnel</package>.
                After enabling <package>mod_proxy_wstunnel</package> a secondary
                    <code>Location</code> section can be added which explicitly proxies the
                Guacamole WebSocket tunnel, located at
                <uri>/guacamole/websocket-tunnel</uri>:</para>
            <informalexample>
                <programlisting>&lt;Location /guacamole/websocket-tunnel>
    Order allow,deny
    Allow from all
    ProxyPass ws://<replaceable>HOSTNAME</replaceable>:<replaceable>8080</replaceable>/guacamole/websocket-tunnel
    ProxyPassReverse ws://<replaceable>HOSTNAME</replaceable>:<replaceable>8080</replaceable>/guacamole/websocket-tunnel
&lt;/Location></programlisting>
            </informalexample>
            <para>Lacking this, Guacamole will still work by using normal HTTP, but network latency
                will be more pronounced with respect to user input, and performance may be
                lower.</para>
            <important>
                <para>The <code>Location</code> section for <uri>/guacamole/websocket-tunnel</uri>
                    must be placed after the <code>Location</code> section for the rest of
                    Guacamole.</para>
                <para>Apache evaluates all Location sections, giving priority to the last section
                    that matches. If the <uri>/guacamole/websocket-tunnel</uri> section comes first,
                    the section for <uri>/guacamole/</uri> will match instead, and WebSocket will
                    not be proxied correctly.</para>
            </important>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="change-web-app-path">
            <title>Changing the path</title>
            <para>If you wish to serve Guacamole through Apache under a path other than
                    <uri>/guacamole/</uri>, the configuration required for Apache will be slightly
                different than the examples above due to cookies.</para>
            <para>Guacamole does not rely on receipt of cookies for tracking whether a user is
                logged in, but cookies are required for the proper operation of the HTTP tunnel. If
                the HTTP tunnel is used, and cookies cannot be set, users will be unexpectedly
                denied access to connections they legitimately should have access to.</para>
            <para>Cookies are set using the absolute path of the web application
                    (<uri>/guacamole/</uri>). If this path differs from that used by Apache, the
                path in the cookie needs to be modified using the
                    <parameter>ProxyPassReverseCookiePath</parameter> directive:</para>
            <informalexample>
                <programlisting>&lt;Location /<replaceable>new-path/</replaceable>>
    Order allow,deny
    Allow from all
    ProxyPass http://<replaceable>HOSTNAME</replaceable>:<replaceable>8080</replaceable>/guacamole/ flushpackets=on
    ProxyPassReverse http://<replaceable>HOSTNAME</replaceable>:<replaceable>8080</replaceable>/guacamole/
    ProxyPassReverseCookiePath /guacamole/ /<replaceable>new-path/</replaceable>
&lt;/Location>

&lt;Location /<replaceable>new-path</replaceable>/websocket-tunnel>
    Order allow,deny
    Allow from all
    ProxyPass ws://<replaceable>HOSTNAME</replaceable>:<replaceable>8080</replaceable>/guacamole/websocket-tunnel
    ProxyPassReverse ws://<replaceable>HOSTNAME</replaceable>:<replaceable>8080</replaceable>/guacamole/websocket-tunnel
&lt;/Location></programlisting>
            </informalexample>
            <para>This directive is not needed for the WebSocket section, as it is not applicable.
                Cookies are only used by Guacamole within the HTTP tunnel.</para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="disable-tunnel-logging">
            <title>Disabling logging of tunnel requests</title>
            <para>If WebSocket is unavailable, Guacamole will fallback to using an HTTP-based
                tunnel. The Guacamole HTTP tunnel works by transferring a continuous stream of data
                over multiple short-lived streams, each associated with a separate HTTP request. By
                default, Apache will log each of these requests, resulting in a rather bloated
                access log.</para>
            <para>There is little value in a log file filled with identical tunnel requests, so it
                is recommended to explicitly disable logging of those requests. Apache does provide
                a means of matching URL patterns and setting environment variables based on whether
                the URL matches. Logging can then be restricted to requests which lack this
                environment variable:</para>
            <informalexample>
                <programlisting>SetEnvIf Request_URI "^<replaceable>/guacamole</replaceable>/tunnel" dontlog
CustomLog  <replaceable>/var/log/apache2/guac.log</replaceable> common env=!dontlog</programlisting>
            </informalexample>
            <para>Note that if you are serving Guacamole under a path different from
                    <uri>/guacamole/</uri>, you will need to change the value of
                    <parameter>Request_URI</parameter> above accordingly.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
</chapter>
