<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<chapter xml:id="using-guacamole" 
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="en"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

    <title>Using Guacamole</title>
    <para>When you visit a Guacamole instance for the first time, you will see the login screen.
        This screen authenticates you with Guacamole, allowing you to use Guacamole to interact with
        one or more remote desktops. Enter your username and password and click "login". Keep in
        mind this is the login for Guacamole, and not necessarily the login for the remote desktop
        you wish to connect to. The username and password you give Guacamole grants you access to
        the Guacamole system only. The usernames and passwords required for the remote desktops are
        independent of this.</para>
    <para>If the correct username and password are provided, a list of available remote desktop
        connections will be presented. This is the list of all connections which you have been
        granted permission to access. If you have used Guacamole in this specific web browser
        before, you will also see thumbnails of recently used connections. </para>
    <para>Clicking on any connection will open that connection in a new window or tab, and multiple
        connections can be used simultaneously.</para>
    <para><indexterm>
            <primary>interacting</primary>
        </indexterm>Guacamole provides an interface for accessing much of the functionality of a
        desktop from within your web browser. The interface is intended to be seamless and
        unobtrusive. Once you open a connection, you will see a realtime view of the remote display.
        You can interact with this display just as you would your normal desktop. Your mouse and
        keyboard will function as if they were connected directly to the remote machine.</para>
    <section xml:id="file-transfer">
        <title>Transferring files</title>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>file transfer</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>You can transfer files back and forth between your local computer and the remote
            desktop if it is supported by the underlying protocol and enabled on the connection.
            Currently, both RDP and SSH have support for file transfer, though with slightly
            different semantics. RDP provides file transfer by emulating a virtual drive, while SSH
            provides file transfer by using SFTP.</para>
        <para>To transfer files to the remote computer, drag the files into your browser window. If
            file transfer is enabled, you will see a notification popup showing upload progress. If
            file transfer is not enabled or not supported, you will instead see a notification with
            an error message describing the problem.</para>
        <para>The method for downloading files from the remote computer depends on the protocol. In
            the case of RDP, you must drag, copy, move, or save the files into the special
            "Download" folder located in the virtual drive. All files dropped into this folder will
            automatically begin uploading to the client, and thus downloading through your
            browser.</para>
        <para><indexterm>
                <primary>guacctl</primary>
            </indexterm>To download files over SSH, you must use the <command>guacctl</command>
            utility. The <command>guacctl</command> utility is included with Guacamole, and allows
            you to initiate a file download or to change the directory in which uploaded files will
            be placed:</para>
        <informalexample>
            <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>guacctl</userinput>
<computeroutput>guacctl 0.8.0, Guacamole SSH session control utility.
Usage: guacctl [OPTION] [FILE]...

    -d, --download         download each of the files listed.
    -s, --set-directory    set the destination directory for future uploaded 
                           files.</computeroutput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>guacctl -d <replaceable>FILENAME</replaceable></userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>guacctl -s <replaceable>DIRECTORY</replaceable></userinput>
$</screen>
        </informalexample>
        <para>You may also create a symbol link or alias to <command>guacctl</command> called
                <command>guacget</command>. When run as <command>guacget</command>, it behaves as if
            the <option>--download</option> option was supplied and initiates a download for each
            file specified on the command line.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="guacamole-menu">
        <title>The Guacamole menu</title>
        <para>Other functions, such as clipboard access and input options, are kept out of the way
            in a sidebar menu which is hidden by default. On a desktop or other device which has a
            hardware keyboard, you can show this menu by pressing <keycombo>
                <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
                <keycap>Alt</keycap>
                <keycap>Shift</keycap>
            </keycombo>. If you are using a mobile or touchscreen device that lacks a keyboard, you
            can also show the menu by swiping right from the left edge of the screen. To hide the
            menu, press <keycombo>
                <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
                <keycap>Alt</keycap>
                <keycap>Shift</keycap>
            </keycombo> again or swipe left across the screen.</para>
        <para>The Guacamole menu provides options for:<itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Reading from (and writing to) the clipboard of the remote desktop</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Selecting alternative methods of typing or controlling the mouse,
                        particularly for use on mobile or touchscreen devices</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Zooming in and out of the remote display</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
        <section xml:id="using-the-clipboard">
            <title>Using the clipboard</title>
            <para><indexterm>
                    <primary>clipboard</primary>
                </indexterm>Right at the top of the Guacamole menu is a text area labeled
                "clipboard" along with some basic instructions:</para>
            <blockquote>
                <para>Text copied/cut within Guacamole will appear here. Changes to the text below
                    will affect the remote clipboard.</para>
            </blockquote>
            <para>The text area functions as an interface between the remote clipboard and the local
                clipboard. Text from the local clipboard can be pasted into the text area, causing
                that text to be sent to the clipboard of the remote desktop. Similarly, if you copy
                or cut text within the remote desktop, you will see that text within the text area,
                and can manually copy it into the local clipboard if desired.</para>
            <para>Guacamole will automatically sync the contents of this clipboard across any other
                open connections within the same browser, thus copying and pasting between
                connections is seamless; you do not need to repeatedly visit the clipboard in the
                menu to copy and paste from one connection to another.</para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="using-the-osk">
            <title>Alternative input methods</title>
            <indexterm xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                <primary>on-screen keyboard</primary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>The menu provides alternative choices for keyboard input beyond simply the
                physical keyboard attached to your computer. In fact, if your computer lacks a
                physical keyboard entirely (such as a mobile phone), these may be absolutely
                required for typing. There are three choices: "None", "Text input", and "On-screen
                keyboard".</para>
            <section>
                <title>None</title>
                <para>Choosing no input method at all means that keyboard input must come from a
                    local keyboard. This is the default option, but may not be appropriate for
                    mobile devices and touchscreen devices that lack a physical keyboard.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Text input</title>
                <para>"Text input" allows input of keystrokes based on the input of text. While not
                    easy to conceptualize, some devices do not actually provide a means of sending
                    traditional keystrokes, but instead provide a means of entering text. A prime
                    example of such a device is a smart phone.</para>
                <para>Many smart phones lack a physical keyboard entirely, and instead provide their
                    own on-screen keyboards to allow typing. When characters are typed through the
                    on-screen keyboard, they appear not through a down/up series of key events but
                    through a single input event. The concept is closer to what happens when you
                    paste text into a text field.</para>
                <para>Choosing "Text input" tells Guacamole to infer keystrokes by tracking text
                    entered through such an input method. Guacamole will determine the combination
                    of keypresses necessary to produce the same pattern of input, including
                    deletions.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>On-screen keyboard</title>
                <para>Certain key combinations are impossible to press within a web application like
                    Guacamole because they are reserved by the operating system (<keycombo>
                        <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
                        <keycap>Alt</keycap>
                        <keycap>Del</keycap>
                    </keycombo> or <keycombo>
                        <keycap>Alt</keycap>
                        <keycap>Tab</keycap>
                    </keycombo>, for example) or by the web browser. If you press one of these
                    reserved combinations, the effect will be observed locally, not remotely, and
                    the remote desktop will receive only some of the keys.</para>
                <para>Guacamole provides its own, built-in on-screen keyboard which allows keys to
                    be sent to the remote desktop without affecting the local system. If the device
                    you're using does not have certain keys which the remote desktop depends on,
                    such as the arrow keys or <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>, you can use the on-screen
                    keyboard for this, too. You can show the on-screen keyboard by selecting the
                    "On-screen keyboard" option from the menu.</para>
                <para>Clicking (or tapping) the buttons of the on-screen keyboard has the same
                    effect as pressing the same buttons on a real keyboard, except that the
                    operating system and browser will not intercept these keypresses; they will only
                    be sent to the remote desktop.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="zooming">
            <title>Scaling the display</title>
            <para><indexterm>
                    <primary>zoom</primary>
                </indexterm>Guacamole will default to shrinking or expanding the remote display to
                fit the browser window exactly, but this is not necessarily ideal. If the remote
                display is much larger than your local display, the screen may be impossible to see
                or interact with. This is especially true for mobile phones, whose screens need to
                be small enough to fit in the average hand.</para>
            <para>You can scale the display on touch devices by using the familiar pinch gesture.
                Place two fingers on the screen and bring them closer together to zoom out or
                further apart to zoom in.</para>
            <para>If your device lacks a touch screen, you can also control the zoom level through
                the menu. The controls for zooming in and out are located at the bottom of the menu.
                The current zoom level is displayed between two "-" and "+" buttons which control
                the zoom level in 10% increments.</para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="using-mouse">
            <title>Relative vs. absolute mouse control</title>
            <para><indexterm>
                    <primary>mouse</primary>
                </indexterm>In the case that your device has a touchscreen and lacks a mouse,
                Guacamole will emulate a mouse for the sake of interacting with remote desktops that
                expect mouse input. By default, Guacamole uses "absolute" mouse emulation. This
                means that the mouse pointer is positioned at the location of each tap on the
                screen.</para>
            <para>Absolute mouse emulation is the most intuitive and tends to be what people expect
                when using a touch device to interact with applications designed for mouse input.
                Each tap on the screen is translated into a left-click at that position.
                Right-clicking is accomplished through pressing and holding your finger on the
                screen. If parts of the remote display are off-screen, you can drag your finger
                around the screen to pan the off-screen parts back into view.</para>
            <para>Although absolute mouse emulation works generally well, a finger makes for a very
                inaccurate pointing device. To address this, Guacamole also provides "relative"
                mouse emulation. Relative mouse emulation provides a way to deal with the need for
                accurate pointer control, when a true pointer device is not present.</para>
            <para>Guacamole's relative mouse emulation behaves similarly to the touchpad present on
                most modern laptops. You drag your finger across the display to move the mouse
                pointer, and tap the display to left-click. The pointer moves relative to the motion
                of your finger. Right-clicking is accomplished with a two-finger tap, and
                middle-clicking with a three-finger tap. The mouse scroll wheel can be operated by
                dragging two fingers up or down.</para>
            <para>Because the relative mouse emulation reserves so many gestures for the different
                mouse buttons and actions, common touch gestures like panning and pinch-to-zoom will
                not work while relative mouse emulation is enabled. Instead, the screen will
                automatically pan to keep the mouse pointer in view, and you can zoom through the
                buttons in the menu.</para>
            <para>In both absolute and relative modes, you can click-and-drag by tapping the screen
                and then quickly placing your finger back down. This gesture only causes the mouse
                button to press down, but does not release it again until you lift your finger back
                up.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="guacamole-admin-ui">
        <title>Administration</title>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>administration</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>Users and connections can be administered from within the web interface if the
            underlying authentication module supports this. The only officially-supported
            authentication module supporting this is the MySQL authentication provider, which is
            documented in a different chapter.</para>
        <para>If you are using the default authentication mechanism, this
            section does not apply to you, and the Guacamole web interface will
            appear as it did in past releases. If, on the other hand, you are
            using the MySQL authentication provider, and you are logged in as an
            administrator, you will see a "Manage" button next to the "Logout"
            button at the top of the screen.</para>
        <informalfigure>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../images/manage-button.png" format="PNG" contentwidth="3in"
                    />
                </imageobject>
                <caption>
                    <para>The "Manage" button</para>
                </caption>
            </mediaobject>
        </informalfigure>
        <para>Clicking this button takes you to an administration screen where
            you can add or manipulate users and connections, depending on your
            permissions.</para>
        <section>
            <title>Managing users</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>user management</primary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>Once at the administration screen, you will see two sections
                displaying all visible users and connections. The visibility of
                these sections depends on your user's permissions. If you lack
                permission to manage users, the user management section will not
                display. The same goes for management of connections.</para>
            <para>To add a new user, type the username of the new user within
                the text box inside the user management section, and click the
                "Add" button. The new user will be added and made available. The
                new user will have no access to any existing connections, no
                administrative privileges, and no password, and will not be able
                to login. You will need to set the user's password first in
                order to allow login.</para>
            <informalfigure>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="../images/manage-users.png" format="PNG"
                            contentwidth="3in"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption>
                        <para>User management interface</para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </informalfigure>
            <para>To edit a user, just click on the user you wish to edit. A small dialog will
                display allowing you to change the user's password, add or remove administrative
                permissions, and add or remove access to specific connections or groups.</para>
            <para>If you have delete permission on the user, you will also see a
                "Delete" button. Clicking this button will permanently delete
                the user.</para>
            <informalfigure>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="../images/edit-user.png" format="PNG" contentwidth="2in"
                        />
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption>
                        <para>Editing a user</para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </informalfigure>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Managing connections</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>connection management</primary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>To add a new connection, click the "New Connection" button. A connection creation
                dialog will appear, allowing you to enter the details of the connection, such as its
                location, parameters, and name. This name should be descriptive, but must also be
                unique.</para>
            <para>Once you click "Save", the new connection will be added, but will initially only
                be usable by administrators and your current user. To add access to the new
                connection to another existing user, you must edit that user, checking the box
                corresponding to the new connection.</para>
            <informalfigure>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="../images/manage-connections.png" format="PNG"
                            contentwidth="3in"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption>
                        <para>Connection management interface</para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </informalfigure>
            <para>Editing a connection works identically to editing a user.
                Click on the connection you wish to edit. A dialog will pop up
                displaying all parameters associated with the connection,
                allowing you to change the protocol, associated parameters, and
                to view the connection history.</para>
            <para>Connections can also be renamed or moved by altering the contents of the "Name" or
                "Location" fields.</para>
            <para>If you have delete permission on the connection, you will also
                see a "Delete" button. Clicking this button will permanently
                delete the connection.</para>
            <informalfigure>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="../images/edit-connection.png" format="PNG"
                            contentwidth="2in"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption>
                        <para>Editing a connection</para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </informalfigure>
            <section>
                <title>Grouping connections</title>
                <indexterm>
                    <primary>connection groups</primary>
                </indexterm>
                <indexterm>
                    <primary>groups</primary>
                </indexterm>
                <para>Connections can be placed within groups for purposes of organization or load
                    balancing. Each group is displayed in connection lists as a "+" symbol followed
                    by its name. The group can be expanded revealing any contained connections or
                    groups. If the group is a balancing group, the group can be used as a
                    connection, and the least-used contained connection will be used.</para>
                <para>To add a new connection group, click the "New Group" button. A connection
                    group creation dialog will appear, allowing you to enter the details of the
                    group. Just as with connections, you can enter the location and name, which
                    should be descriptive and unique. Duplicate names are not allowed.</para>
                <informalfigure>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="../images/edit-group.png" format="PNG"
                                contentwidth="3in"/>
                        </imageobject>
                        <caption>
                            <para>Editing a connection group</para>
                        </caption>
                    </mediaobject>
                </informalfigure>
                <para>You can edit existing connection groups by clicking on them within the
                    administration interface, just like with users and connections. From within the
                    dialog that appears, you can rename, move, and change the properties of existing
                    connection groups.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Balancing vs. organizational groups</title>
                <para>Connection groups can be either "organizational" or "balancing". Each group
                    can contain any number of other connections or groups, but the semantics of the
                    group change depending on the type.</para>
                <para>An organizational group behaves exactly as a folder or directory in a file
                    system. It simply contains connections and other groups, but provides no other
                    behavior. Clicking on an organizational group within a connection list will
                    expand the group, revealing its contents.</para>
                <para>A balancing group behaves as a connection. It dynamically balances load across
                    the connections it contains, choosing the connection with the fewest number of
                    active users. Unlike organizational groups, clicking on a balancing group causes
                    a new connection to be opened. The actual underlying connection used depends on
                    which connection has the least load at the time the group was clicked.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="logging-out-of-guacamole">
        <title>Logging out</title>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>logging out</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>When you are done and wish to logout of Guacamole completely, find the original
            connection interface tab and click the "logout" button. Beware that this will close all
            current connections and end your Guacamole session. </para>
        <para>Note that this is not the same as disconnecting from a single connection. To
            disconnect, simply close the tab or window with the remote desktop in it. Closing a tab
            or window automatically disconnects from the associated remote desktop without logging
            you out of Guacamole completely. </para>
        <para>If you logout of Guacamole, all active connections are closed, and can only be
            accessed by logging in again and reconnecting.</para>
    </section>

</chapter>
