<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<chapter xml:id="using-guacamole" 
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="en"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

    <title>Using Guacamole</title>

    <section xml:id="logging-into-guacamole">
        <title>Logging in</title>
        <indexterm xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <primary>Guacamole</primary>
            <secondary>logging in</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>logging in</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>When you visit a Guacamole instance for the first time, you will
            see the login screen. This screen authenticates you with Guacamole,
            allowing you to use Guacamole to interact with one or more remote
            desktops. </para>
        <para>Enter your username and password and click "login". You will then
            be given a list of available remote desktop connections to choose
            from. If you have used Guacamole in that specific web browser
            before, you will also see thumbnails of the screens of recently used
            connections. </para>
        <para>Keep in mind this is the login for Guacamole, and not necessarily
            the login for the remote desktop you wish to connect to. The
            username and password you give Guacamole grants you access to the
            Guacamole system only. The usernames and passwords required for the
            remote desktops you have access to through Guacamole are
            independent. </para>
        <informalfigure>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../images/login.png" format="PNG" contentwidth="4in"/>
                </imageobject>
                <caption>
                    <para> The Guacamole login screen. </para>
                </caption>
            </mediaobject>
        </informalfigure>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="selecting-a-connection">
        <title>Selecting a connection</title>
        <indexterm xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <primary>Guacamole</primary>
            <secondary>choosing a connection</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>connecting</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>Once logged in, you will be presented with a list of connections.
            Selecting a connection from this list will open that connection in a
            new window or tab. The connection list interface will remain open
            and running in the previous window or tab, as it is the only access
            point for other connections, the clipboard, and settings.</para>
        <para>Multiple connections can be used simultaneously. </para>
        <informalfigure>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../images/connection-list.png" format="PNG"
                        contentwidth="4in"/>
                </imageobject>
                <caption>
                    <para> List of available connections. </para>
                </caption>
            </mediaobject>
        </informalfigure>
        <para>If you don't wish to connect to any desktops, you can also logout
            from this screen by clicking the "logout" button. Beware that this
            will disconnect you from any of your open desktops, if you have any.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="interacting-with-the-desktop">
        <title>Interacting with the remote desktop</title>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>Guacamole</primary>
            <secondary>using</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>interacting</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>Once you open a connection, you will see an image of a desktop.
            You can interact with this image just as you would your normal
            desktop, or any remote desktop client. </para>
        <para>Clicking on parts of the image will affect the remote desktop as
            if you were clicking on the desktop directly. Typing causes keys to
            be typed remotely as if you were using a keyboard connected directly
            to the remote machine. </para>
        <informalfigure>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../images/vnc.png" format="PNG" contentwidth="4in"/>
                </imageobject>
                <caption>
                    <para> An active remote desktop. </para>
                </caption>
            </mediaobject>
        </informalfigure>
        <section xml:id="using-the-clipboard">
            <title>Using the clipboard</title>
            <indexterm xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                <primary>Guacamole</primary>
                <secondary>clipboard</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>clipboard</primary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>The clipboard can be manipulated using the clipboard editor
                accessible near the bottom of the connection list
                interface.</para>
            <para>Web browsers don't provide access to clipboard data, thus true
                synchronization between your local clipboard and the remote
                clipboard is impossible. Instead, the clipboard editor acts as
                an intermediary. You can paste text from your clipboard into the
                editor, and it will be sent to the remote clipboard. If you cut
                or copy text remotely, that text will be visible in the
                clipboard editor locally, where you can then select and copy
                it.</para>
            <para>All open Guacamole connections use this common clipboard, thus
                copying and pasting between connections is seamless; you do not
                need to visit the clipboard editor to copy and paste from one
                connection to another.</para>
            <informalfigure>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="../images/clipboard.png" format="PNG" contentwidth="3in"
                        />
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption>
                        <para> The editable clipboard contents, accessible from the connection list
                            interface. </para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </informalfigure>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="using-the-osk">
            <title>Typing with special keys</title>
            <indexterm xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                <primary>Guacamole</primary>
                <secondary>on-screen keyboard</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                <primary>on-screen keyboard</primary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>Certain key combinations are impossible to press within a web
                application like Guacamole because they are reserved by the
                operating system (Ctrl-Alt-Del or Alt-Tab, for example) or by
                the web browser. If you press one of these reserved
                combinations, the effect will be observed locally, not remotely,
                and the remote desktop will receive only some of the keys. </para>
            <para>Guacamole provides an on-screen keyboard such that key events
                can be sent to the remote machine without affecting the local
                browser. You can show the on-screen keyboard by pressing
                Ctrl-Alt-Shift. Pressing the Ctrl-Alt-Shift again will hide the
                on-screen keyboard.</para>
            <para>Clicking on the buttons of the on-screen keyboard has the same
                effect as pressing the same buttons on a real keyboard, except
                that the operating system and browser will not intercept these
                keypresses; they will only be sent remotely. </para>
            <informalfigure>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="../images/osk.png" format="PNG" contentwidth="4in"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption>
                        <para> The on-screen keyboard. </para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </informalfigure>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="logging-out-of-guacamole">
            <title>Logging out</title>
            <indexterm xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                <primary>Guacamole</primary>
                <secondary>logging out</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>logging out</primary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>When you are done and wish to logout of Guacamole completely,
                find the original connection interface tab and click the
                "logout" button. Beware that this will close all current
                connections and end your Guacamole session. </para>
            <para>Note that this is not the same as disconnecting from a single
                connection. To disconnect, simply close the tab or window with
                the remote desktop in it. Closing a tab or window automatically
                disconnects from the associated remote desktop without logging
                you out of Guacamole completely. </para>
            <para>If you logout of Guacamole, all active connections are closed,
                and can only be accessed by logging in again and
                reconnecting.</para>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="using-touch-devices">
        <title>Using touch devices</title>
        <indexterm xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <primary>touch devices</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>Guacamole can be used on devices that have touchscreens, even when
            those touchscreens are the sole means of input, such as most tablets
            and mobile phones.</para>
        <section xml:id="using-mouse">
            <title>Moving the mouse</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>mouse</primary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>As a finger makes for a very inaccurate pointing device,
                especially for mouse-driven applications designed for precise
                input, the default mode for touch-based mouse input in Guacamole
                is touchpad emulation.</para>
            <para>Guacamole's touchpad emulation is similar in behavior to the
                touchpad present on most modern laptops. Drag your finger across
                the display to move the mouse pointer, and tap the display to
                left-click. Right-clicking is accomplished with a two-finger
                tap, and middle-clicking with a three-finger tap.</para>
            <para>Click-and-drag by tapping the screen and then quickly placing
                your finger back down. This gesture only causes the mouse button
                to press down, but does not release it again until you lift your
                finger back up.</para>
            <para>The mouse scroll wheel can be operated by dragging two fingers
                up or down.</para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="zooming">
            <title>Zooming in</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>zoom</primary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>Many touch-enabled devices have small screens, which makes the
                larger screens of a typical remote desktop hard to see and
                interact with. If you want to temporarily zoom in, long-press on
                the display. This will reveal a rectangular magnifier that can
                be dragged around the screen, revealing detail below it at full
                resolution.</para>
            <informalfigure>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="../images/android-magnifier.png" format="PNG"
                            contentwidth="4in"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption>
                        <para>The magnifier tool in use</para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </informalfigure>
            <para>Tapping outside this magnifier closes the magnifier, while
                tapping inside engages a typing mode.</para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="typing">
            <title>Typing</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>typing</primary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>In most cases, if your device has a hardware keyboard or you
                use a bluetooth keyboard, you will not need to do anything
                special in order to type; you can just press keys and expect the
                same effect you would have on a desktop.</para>
            <para>For devices that lack a hardware keyboard, you need to bring
                Guacamole into "typing mode" by long-pressing on the display to
                bring up the magnifier. Tap on the magnifier to bring up your
                device's on-screen keyboard.</para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="panning">
            <title>Panning</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>panning</primary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>Because Guacamole uses all touch events to drive mouse input,
                the normal gestures for scrolling the screen will not work.
                Depending on how big your screen is, and whether the display is
                currently zoomed, you have three options for panning the screen:<orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Move the mouse</para>
                        <para>Moving the mouse beyond the bounds of the screen
                            of the device will cause the display to
                            automatically scroll until the mouse pointer is in
                            view again. This will only work if the screen is not
                            already fully visible.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Long-press to bring up panning mode</para>
                        <para>If the remote display is already fully visible,
                            long-pressing will not bring up the magnifier, but
                            will instead put Guacamole in a panning mode. Arrows
                            will appear at the sides of the screen, and you can
                            drag around the screen as normal. Tapping on the
                            screen will put Guacamole in typing mode, allowing
                            you to type and use your native on-screen keyboard
                            (if any).</para>
                        <informalfigure>
                            <mediaobject>
                                <imageobject>
                                    <imagedata fileref="../images/android-panning.png" format="PNG"
                                        contentwidth="4in"/>
                                </imageobject>
                                <caption>
                                    <para>Panning mode</para>
                                </caption>
                            </mediaobject>
                        </informalfigure>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Bring up the magnifier, tap to put Guacamole in
                            typing/panning mode, and then drag the screen</para>
                        <para>When in typing mode, dragging your finger on the
                            screen will cause the screen to pan as it normally
                            would. This is useful while typing, especially if
                            what you're typing starts to run off the visible
                            area of your device's screen.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist></para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="changing-settings">
        <title>Changing settings</title>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>Guacamole</primary>
            <secondary>settings</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>settings</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>Guacamole's settings section is located within the connection interface, and affects
            the behavior of all active and future Guacamole connections. Unless specified otherwise,
            changing a setting affects current Guacamole connections immediately.</para>
        <informalfigure>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../images/settings.png" format="PNG" contentwidth="3in"/>
                </imageobject>
                <caption>
                    <para>Guacamole settings, accessible from the connection list interface. </para>
                </caption>
            </mediaobject>
        </informalfigure>
        <section xml:id="disabling-sound">
            <title>Disabling sound</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>audio</primary>
                <secondary>disabling</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>sound</primary>
                <secondary>disabling</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>disabling sound</primary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>Sound can sometimes cause problems if your browser is too slow
                or if you lack sufficient network bandwidth. In some cases,
                browsers do not actually support sound, but misreport that they
                do to Guacamole, causing wasted bandwidth when Guacamole sends
                audio data that can't actually be played.</para>
            <para>To disable sound, check the "Disable sound" checkbox in the
                settings section.</para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="disabling-auto-fit">
            <title>Disabling auto-fit of the display</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>auto-fit</primary>
                <secondary>disabling</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>disabling auto-fit</primary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>Normally, scrolling around the screen is troublesome and
                distracting if the remote display you're using is larger than
                the display of your device. Because of this, the remote display
                will automatically fit itself to the available space by default.
                If this is undesirable, you can manually disable this on a
                per-browser basis in the settings section.</para>
            <para>To disable auto-fit, uncheck the "Auto-fit display to browser
                window" checkbox in the settings section.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="guacamole-admin-ui">
        <title>Administration</title>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>administration</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>Users and connections can be administered from within the web interface if the
            underlying authentication module supports this. The only officially-supported
            authentication module supporting this is the MySQL authentication provider, which is
            documented in a different chapter.</para>
        <para>If you are using the default authentication mechanism, this
            section does not apply to you, and the Guacamole web interface will
            appear as it did in past releases. If, on the other hand, you are
            using the MySQL authentication provider, and you are logged in as an
            administrator, you will see a "Manage" button next to the "Logout"
            button at the top of the screen.</para>
        <informalfigure>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../images/manage-button.png" format="PNG" contentwidth="3in"
                    />
                </imageobject>
                <caption>
                    <para>The new "Manage" button</para>
                </caption>
            </mediaobject>
        </informalfigure>
        <para>Clicking this button takes you to an administration screen where
            you can add or manipulate users and connections, depending on your
            permissions.</para>
        <section>
            <title>Managing users</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>user management</primary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>Once at the administration screen, you will see two sections
                displaying all visible users and connections. The visibility of
                these sections depends on your user's permissions. If you lack
                permission to manage users, the user management section will not
                display. The same goes for management of connections.</para>
            <para>To add a new user, type the username of the new user within
                the text box inside the user management section, and click the
                "Add" button. The new user will be added and made available. The
                new user will have no access to any existing connections, no
                administrative privileges, and no password, and will not be able
                to login. You will need to set the user's password first in
                order to allow login.</para>
            <informalfigure>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="../images/manage-users.png" format="PNG"
                            contentwidth="3in"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption>
                        <para>User management interface</para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </informalfigure>
            <para>To edit a user, just click on the user you wish to edit. A
                small dialog will display allowing you to change the user's
                password, add or remove administrative permissions, and add or
                remove access to specific connections.</para>
            <para>If you have delete permission on the user, you will also see a
                "Delete" button. Clicking this button will permanently delete
                the user.</para>
            <informalfigure>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="../images/edit-user.png" format="PNG" contentwidth="2in"
                        />
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption>
                        <para>Editing a user</para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </informalfigure>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Managing connections</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>connection management</primary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>To add a new connection, type the name of the new connection
                within the text box inside the connection management section,
                and click the "Add" button. This name should be descriptive, but
                must also be unique. The new connection will be added, but will
                initially only be usable by administrators and your current
                user. To add access to the new connection to another existing
                user, you must edit that user, checking the box corresponding to
                the new connection.</para>
            <informalfigure>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="../images/manage-connections.png" format="PNG"
                            contentwidth="3in"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption>
                        <para>Connection management interface</para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </informalfigure>
            <para>Editing a connection works identically to editing a user.
                Click on the connection you wish to edit. A dialog will pop up
                displaying all parameters associated with the connection,
                allowing you to change the protocol, associated parameters, and
                to view the connection history.</para>
            <para>If you have delete permission on the connection, you will also
                see a "Delete" button. Clicking this button will permanently
                delete the connection.</para>
            <informalfigure>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="../images/edit-connection.png" format="PNG"
                            contentwidth="2in"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption>
                        <para>Editing a connection</para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </informalfigure>
        </section>
    </section>

</chapter>
